This was a joke. Ooh.
There he is.
Are we all set? Streaming?
All right, thank you.
Okay, welcome to the Rocks, Mineral, and Metadata
session.
I was not planning to be hosting this, so bear with me.
So this is some slides prepared by
Ben Norton from Yale Peabody.
And so he just has some introductions to some work that we have done in this space,
which we'll run through real quick before we move on to the talks.
So
according to Ben's notes, this strategy follows the collections workflow.
So data manager, data mobilization-- or excuse me, data capture,
data mobilization, and data distribution
carried out by the community that binds those phases into one cohesive workflow.
Each of those four components is addressed by a specific activity.
Capture, the collections management system was addressed by GeoSpecify, now part of
Specify 7.12. Mobilization, the ETL
pipelines and data standards by the Mineral Extension and Darwin Core group.
Distribution, the sharing and discovery portals by the Geological
Collections Data Portal, and the GeoSpecimens platform.
And by community, by outreach at every step along the way, from
targeted review
to this symposium.
So this symposium is really about better integrating geological collections
into the TDWG world.
And here is how that strategy has played out.
In November of 2022, Ben submitted a SwissCall net proposal
integrating geoscience collections into Specify software to extend
Specify for earth sciences collections.
That same month, in connection with GeoSpecify, the TDWG executive
approved the Mineralogy Extension Task Group charter.
In July of 2025, the GeoSpecimens portal launched with
additional support from the TDWG Community Support Fund as a proof of
concept for the mineralogy extension terms and the compound specimen model.
This symposium is the first focus solely on earth science collections in more than
10 years. And in October, the mineralogy extension is ratified,
integrating into both Darwin Core and the Darwin Core Data Package.
None of this happens without people.
Rachel Walcott, who is here today and will be speaking, has been integral to nearly
all of these activities, and credit where it's due.
EFG, the ABCD Extension for Geosciences, laid the
path.
Without it, this mountain would have been a far harder climb.
So thank you to the Specify team, consortium members, and the
SCC GeoAdvisory Committee, to our colleagues at the National
History Museums in Bern, Geneva, Basel,
Lausanne, and St. Gallen,
to the Mineralogy Extension Task Group, and the 11 specialists who served as
community reviewers,
to the Paleo Data Working Group, to the institutions that supported this work,
and special thanks to Erica Krimmel and John
Roache.
And to the dozens of institutions that provided feedback, answered
questions, vetted ideas, and provided us data.
With that, let's get to the talks. We're going to start off with
Holly Little, if I can find my pointer.
Oh.
Oh, for speakers, Gary in the green shirt here in the front is going to be
keeping time. He'll give you warnings at five minutes and two minutes,
and then increasingly frantic hand signals if you go past
time. Is that good, Gary?
Yeah.
Okay. So keep an eye on Gary.
Yours is a PDF?
Yes.
I don't know how to start it as the
full screen.
Okay.
It didn't want to do the first slide.
No, I just tested the PowerPoint.
Oh, yeah.
Was it Control + Click?
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you. All right. So Holly, take it away.
Well, let me see if I know how to use this.
I do not.
Oh, great.
Does it work?
It's supposed to.
Want to try it? Oh, you can also do the arrows and the keyboard.
I tried that.
Up and down.
Maybe up and down.
I did.
How do I move my slides?
There.
Do I have to scroll?
Hit down.
Click?
No.
That's really big.
Try up and down.
Wait. Yeah. What did you do?
Up and down.
Okay. Thank you.
Good? Okay. Good morning, everybody. I'm Holly Little.
I'm the Informatics Manager in the Department of Paleobiology at the Smithsonian
National Museum of Natural History.
I'm here on behalf of my colleagues listed here, including Talia, who's in the
room,
to talk about implementation of the new Darwin Core term material
entity type for paleontology collections
So just to give you a little bit of idea of the journey we're going to go on, I'm
going to give you some background, some examples of paleo specimens, and then
we'll briefly talk about the
vocabulary we're proposing for the term.
So, as many of you are probably very familiar, when you're publishing data in
Darwin Core,
one of the best ways to distinguish what kind of material you're talking about from
a natural history collections is the term basis of record.
Anyone mobilizing data up to this point has likely been using that
term, and if you're coming from a paleo collection, you would be using the
value fossil specimen to distinguish paleo collections when you're
publishing your data.
That, of course, is very important when you're looking at something like GBIF, the
aggregating data from many different sources,
to be able to distinguish what that record actually
represents. So if you were looking up a dog,
and you didn't have basis of record, there are
some clues, of course, for being able to distinguish between different
things, but it does help a lot for those initial filterings when you're doing
your search, to be able to distinguish between a fossil specimen, a
preserved specimen, a human observation, or, as is very
common,
records with no images to give you a clue of what you're thinking about,
so fossil specimen there.
Recently, however, with ratification of the new Darwin Core
terms in the Darwin Core Data package, we have new things to consider.
So the introduction of
an option to be a more material-focused data set
introduces the material entity category term and the material
entity type term, both of which are proposed to be used with a very
strict controlled vocabulary.
So we can think about how we might use
those to serve the same purpose as basis of record, but
also possibly extend how well we are able to describe
what those records represent in a fossil collection.
So material entity has a very clear suggestion,
replacing basis of record, possibly, which is either fossil or
fossilized. And then material entity type is meant to be a
more specific,
less broad term, but there's a lot of wiggle room for
how nuanced you want to be with the vocabulary that we might want to use with
material entity type. So the question that we've been asking ourselves is
how granular do you want to be with the vocabulary that we
could use with material entity type now that we can go beyond just
saying something is a fossil?
Early vocabularies proposed for this term included the ones
highlighted in yellow here, macro fossil, meso fossil, micro
fossil, and oversized fossil.
But through our discussions and with some of the examples I'll show you,
we've found that those are not granular enough and don't
actually help you distinguish some of the things you might want to distinguish when
you're thinking about the end users trying to search this data and understand
what your records represent.
So the process that we've gone through with this vocabulary,
we realized that we had this really wonderful opportunity to really
refine what the discoverability of fossil records are in aggregators
like GBIF
by using these terms.
We've gone through a process to gather feedback from various stakeholder
communities, including the Paleo Data Working Group that Adam mentioned,
researchers at a variety of institutions, but in particular, we had a session at
my museum, the Smithsonian Natural History Museum.
We had a session with the TADWIG Earth Sciences and Paleobiology interest group
earlier this spring during the TADWIG working sessions, and now we're presenting it
to you.
After this, we're hoping to finalize what our formal
proposed vocabulary is, and get that incorporated
into the Darwin Core documentation and implemented for use, which, of course,
is another journey of challenges ahead.
So important background for how we thought about scoping this controlled
vocabulary.
It was very important to us that we should use terms that prioritize something our
community is already used to using within their collections as they describe
it.
And also terms that would help improve not only the
discoverability in something like GBIF, but also the management and
digitization and research of that material,
depending on which audience you're thinking about.
The terms,
I already said that.
Also importantly, when we get to the proposed terms,
there is a little bit of perceived overlap between them, and that's a little bit
intentional because we're trying to align to those
vocabularies that are already in use across paleo collections and what best
serves the purposes that we found as we were going through this process.
Also importantly, these terms only cover paleo collections.
The geology portion of this is covered
in a similar tree, but in a different vocabulary, which Ben has been
working on.
So to get into the examples.
Shown here are two fossil insect specimens.
If someone was to go to GBIF and search by taxonomy trying to
find a particular fossil insect, unless you had images,
which are not readily apparent when you're doing search, you can't search
based on what image you're using.
You might not understand the difference between one fossil insect
specimen that is in amber and one fossil insect specimen that is a
compression fossil shown here on your right.
And the end result of that might be that the person doing that search is
trying to find one or the other for a very particular purpose.
And there's not really a way to easily filter the
resulting records down without ...
possibly using something like this material entity type controlled vocabulary
that we're proposing.
There are a few other terms in Darwin Core that I'll talk about in a little bit
that may help you get there, but they're not
usually readily available in the search interface. They're not highlighted.
Some of them aren't indexed. So using those to get to the same
result isn't as straightforward as having a good vocabulary
for material entity type.
Similarly, for bivalves, all of these, although they are all
bivalves and have some similarities,
could be used for different purposes, both for research and collections management.
And there, again, is not necessarily an easy way to distinguish
them in the records as you're doing your search.
So we have bivalves in matrix,
many bivalves in matrix, one in matrix, a lot,
and then a stratigraphic sample.
Another example, so these are all forams.
Forams come in many forms.
You may just have a bulk sample, a pick sample, many
forams on a slide, one foram on a slide, and sometimes
forams are actually macrofossils, and you don't need a microscope
to see them.
So you can imagine if you were thinking about an imaging workflow, this is kind of
important to know.
And then also for plants,
we have an imprint of the fossil here, so
a mold,
I think,
a body fossil, and then disarticulated in
matrix with many elements there of all the same
similar type of fossil.
Thank you.
So you can imagine if you're a researcher, you're trying to think of trilobite
mass mortality,
and you were searching in GBIF, you would not necessarily be able to
tell if you had a slab with many trilobites or
distinct, separate trilobites. And to study that
particular question, what you actually need is that slab
to then go and think about does that actually represent the question that you're
asking.
And then similarly, if you're in collections and you're trying to do photography
of vertebrate fossils, you can imagine that taking pictures of
all of these things would be a totally different workflow.
So having a good vocabulary for this term actually would help you be able to
know what you can sort on and how you can plan your
imaging project.
So in Darwin Core and some of the other TDWG standards, there are terms that
help to get at this problem,
but they, like I said before, are not necessarily indexed
or readily available for search. So we have the two new
terms we've talked about. Darwin Core preparations is one that gets mentioned a
lot, but if you're familiar with that term, you know it gets used in
50 million different ways. It does not have a controlled
vocabulary, and it's definitely not indexed in a way that's very
searchable.
Counts help you. Taxonomy, of course, helps you.
One thing that we talk a lot about in the paleo community is the need for a
morphology term that doesn't even exist yet.
And then Latimer Core has two that would help as well, but those have not been
adopted into Darwin Core.
So using the material entity type really answers this question for
us in an initial search and filter for when you're trying to find the
right fossil records for your
collection
or for your search. So we have a QR code
here for a document that outlines
the vocabulary terms that we're proposing.
It's just this initial set. We do
think that this is likely going to be a hierarchical
vocabulary with two concept levels.
So what we're proposing right now is just the
first level of
values, and then nested under that is probably a
more informal list of terms that could be used to be more specific within those if
you want to do that, if you want to adopt it to that level, or you need that
within your own system.
And so those level two are included just to give some context and help understand
how we organize this
in the document. And with that, I will leave you with
our-- Is this two minutes? Okay, good.
I thought you were holding up the end sign.
So this is, again, the list of terms that we're proposing with images from the talk
of how we would align those images to those terms.
And I'm happy to leave it with questions there.
Everybody's taking a picture.
I'll go back to that slide for a second, but special thanks to Paleo Data
Working Group, the TDWG Earth Sciences and Paleobiology Interest Group, and
a recent workshop we had with other collections folks in the
US.
And if you have any questions, Thalia and I are here. Erica's online.
We're happy to talk about it. We, of course, really want your input.
Please go to this QR code, let us know what you think.
Yeah.
We have time for one question if anybody
has one.
Sure.
Is there any chance that Darwin Core will take
on the
vocabularies from Latimer Core, or is it better to
use them both separately?
It's a good question.
Microphone.
Yes, I can. So Patricia asks if there's any chance that Darwin
Core would possibly adopt the two terms from Latimer Core.
We haven't actually asked. I think it is a potential, and it's something that we
plan to put on the table as a possible proposal,
but we haven't formalized what a proposal would look like.
So if people want to talk about that too, we'd be happy to.
So the Paleo Data Working Group has spent years talking about what is a
preparation, what's morphology, what's a preservation.
So
we've got a lot of thoughts.
Okay. Thanks, everybody.
Thank you, Holly.
Okay.
I always appreciate when people are running these in the big plenary sessions, how
good they are at segueing between talks.
That's not me. I'm just going to introduce the next talk if I can find my mouse,
which I'm having a lot of trouble seeing on this screen.
Okay.
So our next talk
is Teresa Miller, who's going to be talking about extending Specify
7 for geology collections. Welcome, Teresa.
Thank you.
Do you have a mic?
Yes, I do.
Oh, yes. Thank you.
Oh, speakers, just make sure you get mic'd up before your talk.
That's how good the mic is. You couldn't even tell I had it on.
Okay. Hello, everyone. My name is Teresa Miller with the Specify Collections
Consortium. I am here today to talk about GeoSpecify,
which is a collaborative initiative
between
curators, collection managers, data programmers, all to
try to extend the existing Specify data model to support
geology collections as well.
I'm just going to move on. The idea was
that we wouldn't create a separate system to support-- I'm just going to move away
from that, a separate system to support geology, but it would be
incorporated into the existing data model.
So natural history collections and earth science collections could all use the
same system. So it's all in the same platform, all in the same
standards, so everybody in your institution could be in the same
system.
Oh, it's showing me the future one. Okay.
So our project was led by Beta Hofmann
at the Natural History Museum of Bern, James Beach at the Specify
Collections Consortium, and Ben Norton.
It was funded by the Swiss Academy of Sciences and their SwissCollnNet grant.
It was done in two phases. The first phase was led by Ben Norton, started
in 2023, and the idea of his phase was to come up with a
conceptual data model based on real workflows.
So he worked with
collections throughout Switzerland to try to come up with their requirements and
their needs. He also came up with a classification system.
Phase two, led by the Specify Collections Consortium,
worked on really defining the requirements for such a data model.
What are the actual workflows? Going and getting use cases from different
people throughout Switzerland and throughout the wider community to
see what their actual needs are. How do they use specimens?
How do they perceive of specimens?
And then with that, we come up with a design and implementation
for the data model.
We worked with the Swiss collaborative team, which had representatives
from four
natural history collections, or four collections throughout
Switzerland in Bern, Basel, Geneva, and Lausanne.
We met with the team regularly to really talk to them and get
their feedback, hear from them how they work with collections,
hear from them what their concerns were and what their needs were.
Then we went to the broader community with our GeoSpecify advisory
committee. These are representatives from not only members of the Specify
Collections Consortium, but the community at large, to
really get a more diverse set of needs and requirements from
all people working with geoscience collections.
In addition to that, we did, I say we, I wasn't involved, I
didn't get to go, an intensive requirements gathering trip
where members of the Specify team got to go to the four
major
history museums throughout Switzerland and really talk to the
people there, get into the collections, see how they work with the collections, see
what their needs were, talk to them about how they do classification and what their
needs are. How do they do searches on the different
times?
When they're cataloging something, what are the things that they need to be able to
catalog? They need to be able to warn their people that something's heavy.
They need to be able to warn them that it's toxic.
So all of those things went into our design.
So with that, we extended Specify in several key ways.
So let's start by looking at the trees.
I'm going to apologize now, I've never done this in under 20 minutes, so I'm trying
to rush. So Godspeed to us all. So
Specify already has six
different trees, and these are
visual representations of hierarchical data.
For GeoSpecify, we really focused on three of these trees.
So we start with the chronostratigraphy tree, which Specify has
always had, but we extended under GeoSpecify.
And I'm really excited to talk about this because last time I explained it, it was
all entomologists and botanists, they didn't care.
So they didn't understand how cool this is, that you can now see the end and
start date in chronostratigraphy.
So when you're looking at the tree, you really know what the dates are that you're
working with. There's a cool little button you can click, and it will
bring up the international chronostratigraphic chart, so you can see the chart when
you're entering the data and really understand it.
The tree is always organized by age, so when you're going through it, you have a
feeling of where everything is in the age.
In addition to that, there's a little checkbox at the bottom, so you
can document chronostratigraphy and biostratigraphy in the same
chronostratigraphy tree. And then when you're searching it, you can say, "Actually,
I only want to see biostratigraphy nodes," and then it will just show you those
nodes in your tree. "I want to see everything," it'll show you everything in the
tree. And then there's a lot of other cool features for the tree, but I can't
explain them to you because we don't have time, that allow you to see the objects
associated and so on.
For lithostratigraphy,
this is another tree that we've always had.
This is a tree that
each individual institution can add their own data to, because
each region is so different and so unique with their own terms and their
own
Lithology, so you can enter that for yourselves.
And then Tectonic Unit was added for GeoSpecify so that
you can really document the tectonic unit of your region.
So each institution can enter their own values since it does differ so
widely between regions.
Then let's move on to the tables. Several new tables were added.
We'll start with Geologic Context, which was already there a little bit, but we
extended it for GeoSpecify. Now, this is really the
backbone of geological description in Specify.
This is the one table that links out to all of the
geo-references. So
you can link out to your lithostrat here, you can link out to your
chronostrat, your tectonic unit, and
biostratigraphy. And the really cool thing is you can also have a start period
and end period for your chronostratigraphy.
So if your object spans a range,
you can document that here and really say it goes from here to here.
We also added
Relative and Absolute Age tables, and we added this as a one-to-many,
meaning that you can have multiple ages for each object.
So you can have multiple relative ages, you can have multiple absolute ages
for one object. And I always remember Beta really
focusing on this when we were talking to him, because one object
might have an age of deposition, it might have an age of metamorphism, it
might have multiple ages, and if you can't document all of that
information, you really lose the context for the object and for the
matrix it was in. So this allows you to document all of that and keep
track of everything.
But now that you have multiple ages, what do you do with it?
And this is my favorite tool, so I'm going to spend more time on it.
So we have extended age queries. Now, extended age queries
allow you to search all of that at one time.
So I mentioned we have the geologic context, and you could put
chronostratigraphy there. Well, you can also put chronostratigraphy in
relative age. But when you're searching, you don't want to search two fields.
Extended age query allows you to search in one,
which is really cool. So it looks at both of those, extended age,
absolute age, and
geologic context for the age you're looking for.
And if that wasn't cool enough, on top of that, you can
add the name. So I could add Jurassic, and it would
transfer that automatically to an age range, so
a time range. So when I say Jurassic, it's actually going to look at the range
associated with that. Or I could be very specific
and put in a range. I could put in something like 15 million years ago, and it will
search that, and it will transfer that to name as well.
So it will consider that when it's doing the search.
I can also put in a range, so I can say 15 million to five million
years ago, and it will search for everything within that range.
But wait, there's more, because this is my favorite tool.
So in addition to that, you can do it strict or non-strict,
meaning if I do it strict, I said 15 million to five million years
ago. Ten million fits in that range.
But if I have an object that's 10 million to two million, that doesn't fit in the
range. So that's not going to come back because I didn't want that back.
I don't want things from two million years ago.
If I do non-strict, it will bring back that data.
So I can bring back things that go over boundaries if I want it to.
So an extremely cool tool.
So let's move on to functionality because I only have five minutes left, and this
is the stuff that my boss really likes, so I really need to focus on this.
So Collection Object Types,
I will admit, is also cool. So Collection Object Types allow you to have different
types of objects in the same collection because as you
know,
minerals have different requirements from rocks, have different requirements from
paleo. All of them are very different.
So you're going to have different attributes that you want to document, different
classification trees. You might have different numbering sequences as well.
So Types allows you to document all of that.
So you can have a specific type and say this type uses this
classification tree. It also uses these forms,
and it also uses this numbering sequence.
Or you could say, "Actually, all of mine use the same numbering sequence," so they
all have different forms, but they use the same numbering sequence.
So it gives you a lot of variation in how you document things.
But it keeps everything in the same collection because as you know,
it often has paleo items and
rocks and minerals all in the same collection. You're responsible for all of those.
So it keeps everything together. Sorry, I'm going to rush through because
probably only have four minutes left.
So
in addition to that, we have new default forms.
So when you first get into Specify, we have these forms that
automatically have the fields that you're looking for, for, say,
mineralogy. So these are basic fields with drop-down
lists that make sense for that discipline type.
You can modify these, you can edit it, you can change things around,
but you can start from a point that
the community has agreed on.
Moving on to COGs.
So Collection Object Groups are, as they say, groups of collection
objects. So you can have multiple objects that are documented and cataloged in
your collection, and groups will put them together.
And so this is what it might look like.
We have one group that
has multiple objects in there. They can be different types.
You can see fossils and minerals and rock all in the same group.
We have three different types of this.
We have Discrete, which are individual items which are separated.
We have Consolidated, which means everything's on the same slab, and
we have Drill Cores, which are drill cores.
So Discrete means objects that
might have been together originally.
They were part of the same dinosaur, or they were part of the same slab originally,
but they got broken apart. So they're not actually connected now that they're in
your collection.
Consolidated means it's all the same object.
So it's all in this one specimen that has minerals and has rocks
and has a fossil in it.
So
it's all considered one thing and is stored together.
These can share collection object or catalog numbers, or they can have
unique catalog numbers, depending on how you want to use it.
Components
let you get even more granular. So components allow you to
document different categorizations or identifications
within the same specimen. So it's one rock, but I want to document all the
different minerals that are in there.
So I want to mark that there's quartz in there, and I want to mark that there's
feldspar in there. I don't know if those ever go together, but you want to mark all
of that together. You can do it as basic as a type,
which tells you what tree to go with, or you can get really complex and say, "I
want to document the percentage that's in this rock.
I want to document the colors. I want to document the attributes about this."
So it allows you to do whatever's right for your workflow.
And you can inherit numbers for those, or you can not assign numbers.
Sorry, I'm rushing because I have probably a minute and a half.
Now,
I want to mention data publishing. This is not new to Specify.
However, we did extend this or plan to extend this for
geology collections as well. Grant is actually giving an amazing talk on
this on Thursday, where he talks about the
changes and modifications we've made to our data publishing system in Specify.
But currently, and in the future, you can export your data
in Darwin Core Archive or export it in RSS feed.
So although Specify is not Darwin Core based, you can export your data
in Darwin Core format.
One of the really cool things, if you've used Specify before, you're a little bit
familiar with this system. So you can build your query, and then you can
choose from a core or an extension.
Once the Darwin or the mineral extension is accepted by GBIF, it will
be one of the options that are there.
So my time is up, which is great, because thank you.
I'm going to queue up the next talk, but if anyone has any questions,
we have time for one quick question while I get the next talk up.
And we'll be around all week, so if anybody has questions,
Grant, can you raise your hand?
And Amy
and I will be around, so just pull one of us aside.
Thank you so much.
It's a virtual presentation.
Yes. It's a, yeah, it's a
MP4.
I successfully opened this twice.
Can I get some help up here,
please?
So the video's up in full screen, but
it's not showing.
Okay, the next talk is
Improving Access to Earth Science Collections Data via GeoCase and the
European Open Science Cloud by Laura Tilley and Patricia
Mergen.
This is a virtual talk, but we're having a little trouble with the sound, so we're
just taking a second to get that sorted out.
Oh, he's looking at-
My name is Laura Tilley.
Oh.
And I hope you all are having a great hybrid conference
in Oslo. So today my talk is on
improving access to earth science collections data via
GeoCase and the European Open Science Cloud.
So I'll be talking about a project that is ongoing that
we have been doing with the C-
So, comparison between specimens from different regions.
They allow interdisciplinary research, so a
geologist, a paleontologist, climatologist, and environmental
scientist can look at the same
specimen and get different types of data and answer broad
questions about global challenges such as climate change
or environmental risks. They have a third
dimension, so this is something that is unique to earth science collections.
So this is deep time, and they really reveal a
history of Earth's evolution far beyond the living
systems today. But there are challenges for the
wider discovery and reuse Beyond the
geological earth science community.
So we know that they have a lot of potential for
supporting and understanding global challenges today,
such as mineral exploration, for example,
environmental conservation, even biodiversity.
But in many cases, they still have low visibility,
so they are unknown beyond the collections community.
Many have inadequate metadata, so missing or
inconsistent scientific context.
So it's hard for researchers to understand the resolution of the data
that the specimens can provide, what type of data they can provide, and
where they are from, so the geographic origins, for example.
They still have limited access. So in some cases, data
is not digitized or published. So this is the reason why
they are potentially underused. But to try and solve this
problem, the Earth Science Group of CTAF and MaSE
and Teltech, we decided to submit a
proposal for a small project
grant of six months under a wider project called
EOSC Gravity. And EOSC Gravity is about providing
use cases and services to the European
Open Science Cloud Federation. Our proposal that we
submitted was called GeoDARA. Its aim is to explore how earth
science collection data can be made more fair, discoverable, and
reusable through GeoCASE and the EOSC Federation.
So we selected
three case studies of specimen datasets,
including pollen, tree rings and foraminifera.
We use these case studies to try and look at how we can
improve the metadata associated with them.
So the descriptors that help researchers discover these
specimens and datasets and to evaluate whether they are
useful are not in their own research.
And we want to
improve GeoCASE, the data model if it
requires, and to publish these case studies through GeoCASE
and then connect to the EOSC node called DataTERRA.
So this is a thematic node that deals with environmental and
observation data, so modern data.
So we want to have a look how past data can support
modern observations. Before I actually move on, so the project
started in May, and it will finish in November.
So it's a six-month project, and we're halfway through it.
But just to go into detail about DataTERRA.
So DataTERRA is a thematic node of EOSC, and it
provides access to a wide range of environmental and
earth science data. So it includes data from earth
observations, satellite, climate, and environmental sciences,
even biodiversity. And as I've mentioned before, GeoDARA wants to
explore how collection data can be
connected to this type of modern data and be
interpretable, so for wider use and integration into these
wider datasets. And the aim is that we hopefully
will allow more long-term potential to connect past
environmental records with present day observation data.
So just a little bit of detail on the three case studies that we have.
So we called around the
earth science community to see if there was available datasets
that could be useful. We gathered some pollen records from
Estonia. So these are quite useful for past vegetation and
climate to have a look at changes in land cover and environmental change.
So they are high-resolution datasets from the Quaternary.
We have tree ring records from the University of Helsinki, which
provide climate data from the past
7,500 years, and they're from the Finno-Scandinavian region.
They provide detailed
oxygen and carbon isotopes to
understand the carbon cycle during thousands of years ago,
and to provide dendrochronology information, which can also provide
information on high-resolution environmental
changes, including volcanic eruptions that could be useful
with modern observation datasets.
Finally,
some foraminifera datasets from NHM London.
These are from the HMS Challenger material.
They represent recent and Pleistocene ocean
sediments, and useful information we can get out these include ocean
anoxia, so ocean ventilation
events and climate change. So what we have been doing with
these
different case studies is to have a look at the metadata
concepts that should be associated with them, how to describe them,
the objects type, the taxonomy, the geographic
origin, the age, the depositional environment, and also the
provenance. So the data source, where is it originally
collected from, but also where is the data stored originally.
What we are finding out. So within the collection community,
we commonly use the ABCDEFG standard or the
Darwin Core standard for describing
specimens. However, in DataTERRA,
they are more describing datasets and not individual
specimens, and they use a metadata schema called
DCAT, which is rich, but
it doesn't allow to provide information at the individual specimen level.
So we've been trying to have a look at the differences between
all those different metadata schemas and trying to see how
we can map the different concepts or needed
metadata descriptors so that the information about the
specimens are useful And can be
used by different researchers, but also
how we can connect GeoCase, which will provide more
richer specimen-level information, and then map that to the
higher-level DCAT description of
datasets, which will be shown through DataTerra. So the next steps.
So we are in the middle of completing the metadata assessment that I've just
talked about, so mapping across the selected case studies.
We want to improve the datasets, so the case studies,
and possibly the data model of
GeoCase, and then publish those datasets through
GeoCase. The deliverable of the project will be to develop
a showcase of how we describe or use the metadata in
describing the specimens, how we map to
DCAT, and how the data is published through
GeoCase and then connected to
DataTerra. We want to produce a practical
guidance or a training alongside this demonstrator
so that people, in the future, can upload
earth science datasets, and they can be connected to
wider disciplinary
data portals, in a way. Just one final point, that we will have an
online training demonstrator workshop on the 28th of
October and the 29th. So I will send around a registration form
and an agenda, so please keep an eye out for this.
The workshop will include how to clean data and map it to
ABCDFG, and publish through GeoCase, and also
will provide information about DCAT and providing data
to DataTerra, so it'll show the demonstrator.
If you would like some more information as well, you can
please talk to Patricia Megan, who is at the conference in person,
or you can email us
asking any questions about the presentation or about the workshop
itself. But like I said, there'll be more information coming soon,
and I would like to thank you for listening, and again, I hope you have a
great conference. Hello, everyone.
My name is Laura Tilley, and I hope you all are
having a great TED-
Thanks very much, Laura, et al.
We've got time for a question or two,
and Patricia is here to answer.
Are we volunteering Patricia to field questions?
You can opt out, Patricia.
I'm here the whole conference. If there's any questions, let me know.
Okay, so Patricia is here all week, so if anybody has any questions, she is
happy to discuss.
Our next talk
is improving geospecimen provenance and findability at the National
Museums Scotland Scottish Mineral Collection
by Sarah Stewart.
Welcome, Sarah. Thank you.
Thank you. Yes. So I am a PhD student at the
University of Edinburgh,
working in computational chemistry, so this is not overly my field.
But I do work on clay minerals,
just digital clays.
But I did a short two-month internship at the National
Museum Scotland, working on their mineral collection and trying to
improve the provenance of the specimens.
So
the first thing to tell you a bit about is the collection.
The collection is split into two different parts, and I only worked on the Scottish
part.
But within that, there is about 18,000 geospecimens,
and these can contain
multiple minerals, rocks, everything. I worked on the minerals specifically.
It's an old collection of about 200 years of
collecting within Scotland,
and the records can span from different levels of
provenance.
So for instance, you can get one
like the one here that is incredibly specific on where it was found,
right down to the depth level within the mine.
Or you can get one that's slightly less specific that just gives a more broad
area. Or there's ones that just say Scotland,
which is not the most helpful, but it still gives us some information.
But because we have this information, we can potentially enrich it.
There is also a dual legacy problem in that there's two
different sets of records, so I was also trying to reconcile
these.
There are historical records, which are old ledgers that were
transcribed,
and these can contain just your normal historical problems.
And then there's the modern museum records,
which are digitized already,
but they can sometimes contain missing information.
For instance, there's some that are in the older records that aren't in the newer
records.
So I wanted to take both sets and to try
and merge them together.
And so to do this, I took three sources
and did one workflow on them all. So first, I took the modern
and historical records and merged them into one, where I looked at
any duplicate ones, reviewed them, and earmarked any issues.
Then I went to something called MinDat, which is
a
crowdsourced open access mineralogy database for
the entire world, and also other planets as well.
It has information on minerals, localities, species.
It's also linked to a fossil database,
and
all the records contain coordinates, which was the important thing we
wanted.
So I took the
merged datasets and got the unique localities.
Then I went to MinDat,
took out all of the Scottish localities,
I evaluated them, ensured that they were correct, and then I
tried to match any of the Scottish
values from MinDat that contained coordinates to the ones that we had
from the museum, so that we could add this extra information
to the specimens that we have.
And if you're interested, I do have all of the scripts that I used
to access MinDat available online
at that QR code. It will come up again at the end.
And if you have any issues, you can always email me.
My email is on the link,
and I can help with anything.
So how does this map onto
taking a record and making it into a new, more updated
version?
So
I merged them to harmonize the records, made
sure everything had a
record number,
and then I was also able to get out the IMA species
name to ensure that, because some of them are historical, that have different
names,
and I got out the Dana & Stre ん と values, which are
labels of different mineral classifications.
Then I took out the unique localities, and I separated them
from a really long string into different values at different levels,
which makes searching a lot easier.
Then I matched them to the MinDat records, which gave
us coordinates,
and I evaluated all the MinDat
localities to tell us what is it. Is it a vien?
Is it a river? Is it a mountain?
And give these specificities and also
how the coordinates should be treated.
For instance, for a mine, you get an endpoint, which is the opening of the
mine, whereas for a mountain, usually they give the top of the mountain.
So just more information about the collection.
All of this was done through scripting and also some manual review.
And the systematic processing revealed
some
underlying problems that I could then flag and
easily tell the curators what needed to be fixed.
So there was about, as I said, 18,000 specimens, but
26,000 records, so a little bit of a disparity there.
There was about 1,000 that didn't have IDs.
There were 15,000 that were duplicates that needed
some sort of triaging done. Either there were issues between the duplications
or sometimes they were perfect duplicates, which was great for me.
And I ended up with a list of 16,000 validated specimens.
So just to show that automated pipelines can be really
powerful at finding out these issues in
a pretty fast way.
It took me, as I said, I did all this in two months
of work, but to actually run and write some of these scripts
took a day or so.
So to speak more about the provenance, everything was treated as a
spectrum.
So the highest
level, the broadest, was either the country
or then the next was county. So there's, I think about
36 in Scotland of varying sizes, from a city
to the Highlands of Scotland, which are very large.
Then we get down to more of a region within that county or a loch,
which is just a lake in Scotland.
Then you can get even lower to a town, a parish, a hill,
or to a very specific spot,
such as a quarry or a mine.
And
the museum documentation can contain all of this information,
but quite often what we do find is in an external database, such as
MinDat, this level of detail is flattened.
So this is also something that we can give back to them.
So we wanted to keep this hierarchical indexing so that
there's better searching available.
So MinDat, this was not just a one-way street
of us taking all of the data that they had. We also give back.
So what we at the National Museum had to offer
was 18,000 specimens,
200 years of historical records, curatorial notes.
And so we were able to give to MinDat 900 new
species, 475 existing localities,
and also almost 2,000 new localities that did not
exist before.
From
MinDat, we were able to gain
just over 5,000 new Scottish
specimens.
They have a modern cyber infrastructure in which
everything is a lot more searchable. It's all publicly available.
And I was also able to get some mineral coverage information.
And I should also note that in my processing of MinDat
information, I added coordinates to 52 that did not exist,
and I also corrected 33. So don't take everything at face value.
So for mineral coverage, this was another aspect that I was able to do because
we had this large dataset.
And I also used a book that was written
and published by the Museum
of minerals that are in Scotland. And I was able to see
That there were 366
minerals that were not in the Scottish collection that have been identified by
either MinDat or the book as having existed in Scotland.
And interestingly, I was also able to find that there were 11
minerals that the museum had in their collection but did not exist
elsewhere as knowingly being from Scotland.
So in conclusion, the systematic workflow
automated a lot of heavy lifting.
So yeah, as I said, everything here was done by Python script,
and then some overview of that.
The museum was not passive in this.
We were able to give back to the online community
to enrich their records and to correct things.
And this workflow is also fully transferable, specifically the
MinDat information,
to other collections and to other sections.
So as I said, MinDat has records linked to fossils,
so that's all the information there.
And this is a lovely heat map that I was able to make of all of the
specimens that now have
coordinates.
And I would just like to say thank you to my PhD supervisor for letting me
spend two months not working on my PhD,
and to Rachel and Emily from the museum, who
did all of the curatorial stuff for this and answered many annoying
questions from me.
And to my funders,
the E4DTP,
funded by the Natural Environment Research Council.
And yes, all the scripts are available here on GitHub.
There's documentation on there for how to use everything.
But as I said, if there's any issues, feel free to email me.
I'm always on my laptop, as you will see.
So yeah. Thank you.
Okay. We are running a few minutes ahead, so we do have time for questions.
We're about five minutes ahead.
Mm-hmm.
If nobody has any questions, I can start.
So we've tried to do a little bit of similar
matching. I'm at the Smithsonian Institution's Mineral Sciences Collection.
One issue that we've run into with this kind of matching is ambiguous mine
names. So for example, if you go up into Alaska and you say, "Oh, it's a
King Mine," well, then there's
N King Mines, and where N is kind of a big number.
So how did you handle situations like that? Were they handled by your processing?
Were they omitted?
So I didn't run into any issues like that, thankfully.
Okay.
But yeah, so there was this step where I had to evaluate all of the
things from MinDat,
because there were some that had widely different
coordinates from where they actually should be, the complete opposite side of the
country.
But there's loads of notes for that, thankfully, and the people at
MinDat were really helpful. And within the museum,
so there's some places in Scotland that have the same name, but you can tell if you
go backwards in the hierarchy, for example, with the county, then you can say,
"Oh, it's this one, not a different one." So with all of the
matching...
I should say, this is all of the very complete matches where
everything fully matched, although there can be some things that
were missed out.
And then I also have a list of partial matches,
and of things that were like, "You need to go and check that."
So automating can definitely speed things up.
But yeah, whenever you come to issues of duplicate names, that's when
you need an actual person to go in and say, "No, this is what it actually is."
Okay. Thank you.
Are there any other questions? Sam?
Yeah. Continuing on this subject, we had a similar issue.
We did a similar exercise as well with
seeing if we had names of mines and hills, and
we tried to hold it against MinDat to see if we have matches.
But then we also had a lot of local names,
names that differ between
the
name written on the label, which could be in Dutch or could be in Latin or another
type of name, or an Italian name,
and the English name that is in MinDat.
So we had a couple issues there as well that we had a hard time--
and often we only had the names, so not the complete hierarchy, which will probably
make it a bit easier.
But I'm definitely interested in looking at the scripts and see how you kind of
tackled this
tricky bit. Yeah.
Yeah, there was a lot of time I spent with old maps
looking for random names that some guy had called a hill.
But thankfully, we had annotated maps
from that guy.
And also in the matching,
because we do have some places in Gaelic and some in English,
I included more of a fuzzy match, so things didn't have to be completely
specific.
And also, I
added in some translational words.
So whenever I was parsing out unique localities from the museum
records, it would then go through those and correct,
or not correct, but change the spellings or
the name from Gaelic to English if it was known.
But all of that was also flagged, so all of these outputted as
Excel spreadsheets, and there's always a line that says, "Okay, this was a
duplicate, but
there was spelling changes," or for everything.
Hello.
As the curator involved, I just thought this was a fantastic project to
Do the easy wins automatically, and you always need the person
in the loop in this time, a curator.
But you could also triage the curatorial jobs so that
there are some easy-win curatorial jobs, and then there's some that will take a
whole day per specimen.
So you always need the curator in the loop.
But it stops us having to waste our time on the easy-
Yeah
... automated things.
And also sort the users.
Yeah.
And to your point about giving back to them that it's an open source, it's a
two-way thing. I feel very strongly about that.
Are there any other questions?
If not, thank you again, Sarah. That was a very interesting talk. Thank you.
Our next two talks are going to be virtual, so I'm going to do my best here,
but
we've seen how this has been going.
So hi, everyone. Hi. What's up, everyone?
So
hello, hello. Yeah. It's
good. I didn't have a microphone. All right.
So, everybody always asks me, when do I sleep?
Well, apparently it's the morning of the symposium. I submitted abstract for it.
I don't understand why that's-
So, thanks for coming.
That's all. I ran here. Pretty good shape.
I don't know why that video is showing up.
There it is.
Space bar.
Sample registration, which is the subject of this talk.
Today, I'm going to share a little bit about what SESR does and also how SESR
supports earth and biodiversity digital extended specimens.
I want to acknowledge my co-authors on this talk, Natalie Rhea, and our PI,
Kirsten Leonard, and also the collaborators on the SESR project, including
Sapes Cho and Sean Chao.
So to start off, what is SESR? SESR is a large database
of metadata records describing physical samples and specimens.
And these are physical samples and specimens both from curated museum collections
or core repositories or things like that, as well as samples and specimens from
people's personal collections.
SESR's been around for almost 20 years, plus or minus.
It was initially founded in
2004 by Kirsten Leonard, and it's been fully operational
since 2009. Kirsten Leonard is the PI of this project.
She's at Columbia University.
SESR is also the birthplace of the IGSN, which is a globally unique persistent
identifier for samples, and I'll talk a little bit more about what that means in
the next slide.
And while SESR's name says Earth and Extraterrestrial
Samples,
we
host a wide range of sample types
beyond those domains as well. So we have a growing number of
biodiversity records that are stored in SESR,
and even some medical records as well.
Before I get too much further in this, our website is right up there,
geosamples.org. Just a word of warning, we're in the middle of a huge
migration of our database and website right now.
Over the last couple of years, we've been revamping our data architecture and
redoing our interfaces, just trying to modernize the system overall.
And fortunately or unfortunately, that migration is happening this week.
So you probably can't
play around with the database right now.
But if you check back on Thursday or Friday, it should be fully functional again.
And finally, SESR has a good number of users, so over 1,800 users
across all continents and over five million samples registered overall.
Like I said before, one of SESR's main functionalities is that it mints identifiers
for samples. So it's a place where you can go to get a permanent, unique identifier
for your samples or specimens.
The identifier we use is the IGSN, so that's the International Generic Sample
Number, formerly the International Geo Sample Number.
This is essentially a DOI.
While it wasn't always a DOI, DataCite took over management over the last couple of
years, and it got converted into a DOI.
There's a couple of advantages of using an IGSN for your samples as opposed
to just a catalog number,
which I'll talk about
in this talk. But first and foremost, it ensures that the number you're assigning
to your sample is completely unique.
And when you use that number in a paper or in a data set, you can
unambiguously link your research products back to the sample or specimen
from which they came. So this makes it a lot easier for people to find
samples to reuse.
And also it makes it easier for you to show the impact of your collections or the
impact of the samples by finding the network of
resources that they're connected to.
Like I said, SESR is going through a big migration right now.
We're launching this totally revamped database, and so I'll quickly give a
high-level overview of some of the changes that we're making.
First of all, we've really updated our search portal, both in functionality and in
appearance. So this is a screenshot of our old
current search portal.
Our new search portal, first of all, is just much easier to see and
much more aesthetically pleasing.
But we're also using new and improved vocabularies designed by
Steve Richard, which I'll talk about more in a second,
that make it easier to find specific samples
of a certain type or material or things like that.
And we also have improved search for samples collected through a certain
project or initiative. This is my cat, and I've recorded this three
times now, and he keeps interrupting, and I can't keep him out of the room, and I'm
sorry.
Yeah, so improved search, aesthetically pleasing, better vocabularies.
We also have improved landing pages for our samples.
So the landing page is basically the metadata record that comes up
when you click on the link version of a DOI.
So this is our old landing page. Our new sample landing page,
again, more aesthetically pleasing, better layout of windows
in the actual website. And we also have embedded things
like maps that show you where the sample is in the world, and
also links to the sample family, as well as linked resources as
well.
By sample family, I mean if there's sub-samples and
sibling samples. So if one sample came from a core,
the sample family will link back up to the core that it came from and also
to the sibling samples, so other sub-samples from that particular
core.
SESR also has a workbench within it, which is a lightweight
metadata management system for you to curate all of your records.
This is the current/old version of the workbench.
The new workbench, again, more aesthetically pleasing,
and also has a bunch of improved functionality that I don't necessarily have time
to go in here, but improved sample registration systems,
improved metrics for tracking the use of your samples over time,
and improved team functionality, so you can add people to
work on your samples and manage their access to different kinds of metadata editing
and things like that.
So how does SESR support digital extended specimens?
So the most unique thing about SESR is that it mints
PIDs. It mints these unique identifiers that are guaranteed to be globally
unique.
This makes it possible to
build out that chain of related digital
resources related to a sample in a more persistent and more robust
way.
So some of the core things, information that we store in SESR
metadata records, so sample metadata records, are first, that
IGSN. Second, we also store other identifiers and catalog numbers in the
metadata. So if there's a field number or a local catalog number, that's one of
the first things that we ask for in the metadata.
And we also have explicit semantically rich connections to related digital
resources in the metadata. So that screenshot on the right-hand side is showing two
linked resources to a sample.
But not only do those live in the metadata on SESR,
they also get propagated out to DataCite,
which gives you additional functionality and visualization tools to see
the network of related resources here.
So on the left, you see this little
ball and spoke diagram here. This is on DataCite's Data
Commons webpage. And DataCite is making it
possible for you to traverse the network of samples and related
digital materials
through the DataCite Commons. And DataCite also provides some of its
own metrics that you can search through, such as number of times cited, things
like that. So by using the IGSN, by using this PID,
it makes it possible to store all of this related information.
And by propagating it to DataCite, it makes it available for other people
to harvest and improve on that chain
of related resources and showing the
impact and network of your sample and the work that has come out of them.
One of the major improvements that we've made to SESR in this migration is that
we've updated and enhanced the vocabularies that we're using to describe
samples. So we're now making use of the iSamples
vocabularies to describe samples,
which hopefully increases interoperability.
So we're using the Earth and environmental science extension of the iSamples
material vocabulary. This was designed by Steve Richard, and we're
using a light application profile of it.
We've lightly edited it to
pare down the vocabulary so that it's easier to use by our users.
But this is a much expanded vocabulary, using a
couple of thousand terms as opposed to just a couple of hundred, which is what we
were using before.
And this should hopefully make it possible, A, for people to better
describe the samples.
B, it should make it easier for people to search for samples and find the very
specific kinds of samples that they're looking for.
And C, it should improve the interoperability between SESR and any
other system that's using these vocabularies.
SESR's new architecture also better supports the development of extension
vocabularies and fields. So basically, the new database
design makes it easier for us to create forms and
controlled vocabularies for other domains that are not currently using
SESR as extensively. So right now, we're developing a crosswalk
from SESR's schema to Darwin Core,
and also an application profile of sample-related fields from
Darwin Core so that we can better support biodiversity collections.
So we're working with someone at the Illinois Natural History Survey to register
some of their herpetology collection.
And through that work, we're hoping that we can better support other biodiversity
collections as well.
In the future, we're also developing profiles for marine and lacustrine
sampling
communities, so basically people who are working in core repositories.
New profiles for astromaterials and meteorites, and finally, for
tephras, for the tephra community.
Finally, I want to note that I'm the PI of two active grants that aim to improve
how we share and connect sample metadata in the earth sciences and beyond.
One is through the NSF PHAROS program, and the other is from the
IMLS, which is the Institute for Museum and Library Services.
In both of these, we're doing things like running hackathons, running a webinar
series, developing tutorials on curating sample metadata, and also
developing roadmaps for researchers, scholarly publishers,
data repositories, and sample repositories to
improve their metadata curation practices and
metadata sharing practices to make it easier to
connect samples with the things that we make from samples.
So if you're interested in hearing more about these projects or in participating
in our hackathons or webinar series or anything like that, please contact me.
Here's my email address. And again, I want to thank the CSAR team,
including Kirsten, Sapes, Sean, and Natalie.
Natalie particularly really led the way on the redesign of our user
interfaces. She has left us for a less
soft money position, and we're really happy for her there, but very sad for us that
she's no longer working on this
program. Thank you.
Hello, everyone. My name is Laura Tilley, and I hope-
Okay, in addition to the stuff that Andrea mentioned at the end of
her talk, she also runs a
monthly physical samples group through Earth Science Information Partners,
which is a earth science organization located in the United States.
But it does have worldwide participation.
And she's a good resource for these kinds of conversations.
Next, we have another virtual talk, which this time I'm going to
remember to announce the title of.
So this is going to be by Oscar Lindenmeyer, and it's about developing and
implementing relational mineral taxonomy model in Emu for
Museum Victoria's mineral collection.
So I'm Oscar Lindenmeyer. I'm Collection Manager of the
Geosciences collections here at Museums Victoria.
And so the collections I look after include minerals,
gems, rock spores, meteorites, and various kinds
of impactites.
And I'm going to be talking to you today about a project that we undertook over the
last year or so to develop and implement a relational
mineral taxonomy model in Emu, our collection management system,
in order to manage mineral identification data
for our mineral collection.
And so I'm going to run you through
what our previous model looked like, what we set out to do with
developing this new model and why.
Walk through some mineralogy specific considerations
that went into building and designing the new model.
Talk you through how we actually populated a whole lot of new
mineral taxonomy records using the
OpenMindat API,
and then go through some examples of what this actually looks like in
Emu.
So first off, a bit of background on the collections that I look after.
There are over 100,000 specimens across these
four sub-disciplines.
And the largest of these, and by far the most frequently
accessed, is the mineral collection.
We have about 57,000 mineral specimens,
and these represent something like 2,500 distinct
mineral species and include 131 type
mineral specimens,
which is around half of all the type minerals that are lodged in
Australian institutions.
So what did the data structure look like prior to adopting this
new model? Well, something like this diagram here, where
although we had a relational structure for things like multimedia
and sites,
mineral classification and identification information was only stored
locally within each catalog record.
And the eagle-eyed among you might notice that there are some slight
discrepancies in the examples I've given
with the group and class. And so this highlights
one of the problems that we're trying to address.
And what does the structure look like in the new model?
Well, the main difference is that we now have a
taxonomy record for the mineral species vanadinite,
sitting in the taxonomy module. And each of these catalog records is
linking to that shared vanadinite record, which contains a
whole lot of data and metadata about the species vanadinite and
its classification.
And some of this data is being mirrored back into the catalog so
that we can query and view that information where
it's relevant.
So the first consideration I'll talk about when it came to
designing the new model
is mineral classification schemes.
So the fields that we had in a previous model in the
catalog were species, variety, group, and class.
Species and group are essentially analogous to
this new set of fields, species, subgroup, group, and super group.
These are terms adopted and defined by the International
Mineralogical Association in 2009, and wherever
possible, we want to align with the peak body
on mineral classification.
We also have fields for other rank and other value.
And so these are used for handling non-standard classification
records, and also for cases like with the amphibole super
group, where
unusually there is a fourth level of hierarchical classification that's
been defined by the IMA.
I'll talk about series more in the next slide, but we
also have--
previously, we had just one field for class, and nominally
we were using Dana classes, but we weren't really,
partly because the data was quite messy, but also because the Dana
classification
system hasn't been updated since 1997.
And so for anything
post-1997, we'd sort of made it up as we went.
And so what we decided to do going forward was
keep Dana class and Dana code as fields
for legacy reasons, and because that's how the collection is organized
But also alongside those have Stront's Mindat class
and code,
which we use because they capture similar
information and also are being continually updated and are
easy to access and import via the Mindat API.
So the next consideration I'll talk about are solid solution series,
and this is an aspect of mineralogy that we have to contend with when
trying to capture mineral classification data.
A good example of this is the solid solution series
between ferberite, an iron tungstate mineral, and
hubnerite, a manganese tungstate mineral.
And
these have analogous crystal structures and
essentially can vary chemically
completely between
these two end member compositions.
And we have the term wolframite, which is a synonym of that
ferberite, hubnerite series. Anything that sits along that
continuum could be termed a wolframite,
but this is a series name, not a species name, even though historically,
quite often
we have had wolframite put into the species field.
And so what we want to be able to do is efficiently
return
any member of the wolframite series, including the ones that have been
classified as ferberite or hubnerite.
But we want to be able to do this without also including, for example,
some of the other species that are in the wolframite group, so we can't just go to
the next hierarchical classification level and search for the whole
wolframite group.
So
the way we have addressed this
is to have a field that is for series
within mineral taxonomy records,
and one species can be associated with
multiple solid solution series. And so
this is a table, and it can take multiple values.
And so if we were to search for
wolframite
in that field, we would
be able to return both ferberite and hubnerite, which should
have that field filled in as they are part of that series, but also we can
have a record that is only cataloged to the level of a series and doesn't have
the species field filled,
and they will all return when you query on wolframite.
And so there are other examples, like olivine is another very common
one.
So most mineral solid solution series don't have a special name like this,
but often the cases where they do represent lots of historical
cataloging.
And another consideration is that
some species, for example,
mimetic and heterophane
have a solid solution series between them, but sit in
different mineral groups. And so
we need to be able to contend with this, and this is why the
series field sits outside of the main
hierarchical classification.
When it comes to representing chemistry, the main change
is, as with everything else, we're moving these
fields from the catalog to being
within a mineral taxonomy record.
We've also tweaked the names because there was a bit of
historical confusion about
what exactly we meant by formula and elements.
Did we mean
relating to that particular specimen, or did we mean that species in
general?
And so including ideal formula and ideal elements, I think,
clarifies this.
Ideal formula is intended to capture a human-readable
formula
within EMu, and ideal elements is a table which contains
separated elements and can be used for Boolean searching.
One other consideration is that
EMu can't handle subscripts and superscripts, although we were
initially told that it might be able to.
And so you can see here an example of ferrohornblende,
where I've shown you the
formatting that we landed on to still capture
a chemical formula in a human-readable way.
So how do we go about populating a whole lot of mineral
taxonomy records with all these new fields,
and also linking these to the existing catalog records
efficiently?
Well, before we did anything, we made sure to duplicate the
data in the existing fields into our legacy data field, which
is a locked free text field, so that's preserved.
This was before any of the changes in EMu, the new
tab in taxonomy for mineral data had been created.
We began creating these shell records, you can think of them
as, that were taxonomy records that just contained
an IRN in EMu,
a Mindat ID, and a human-readable name.
And using those human-readable mineral names,
we went through and systematically linked
catalog records to these shell taxonomy records.
And so all of this was done before the changes to EMu
were actually implemented. And so we were, I guess,
ready to strike once they were
and populate all of these
mineral taxonomy records once the fields were available.
To actually get the data to populate these fields,
used the open Mindat API
Because we had the Mindat ID as a common unique
identifier, it was relatively easy to extract the relevant
data and map it to
our new mineral taxonomy fields.
And there were about 150 non-standard records for
cases like incomplete classification or legacy
data that had to be created manually, but everything else was able to be done
quite efficiently pulling data from the Mindat API.
So this is what a mineral taxonomy record
looks like in EMu. This is
a tab that was added onto the existing taxonomy module.
So this is the same module that's been used for many years to capture
biological taxonomy data.
And because of this, we have access to some of the functionality developed
for that, including things like fields for
publications and linking to the bibliography module.
I won't go too much into the fields that I've already talked about, but some
additional ones that we have here are their IMA status, so
whether a species is valid and what subcategory
of valid is it. Was it
defined by the IMA? Was it grandfathered?
And also the date that that status is applicable from.
So this has been quite helpful in,
for example, we may have specimens that
have been cataloged as now discredited names.
We don't want to just replace that, but we do want to capture that it
is a discredited species.
And eventually, hopefully, that will be
re-identified as a valid species.
I mentioned that initially we used a notes field to
capture Mindat IDs when creating those
mineral taxonomy shell records.
Going forward, we're going to use some existing functionality in the
taxonomy module,
this table called descriptions, and these are sort of generic properties.
They just have a label and a piece of data.
And so we can, for example, capture
Mindat ID,
and also potentially I'll do some experimenting with capturing
other properties of minerals that we don't
need to have dedicated fields for.
I'm yet to see how useful this will be, but I think it could be quite interesting
and relatively efficient to import using the Mindat
API.
Now going back to a catalog record.
This is our mineral tab and all of the grayed-out
fields, so species, series, subgroup, group,
supergroup, Dana class, other rank, other value,
and ideal formula are duplicating from
the mineral taxonomy record for andradite in this case.
One thing you might notice is that variety
is not part of that mineral taxonomy record, and so this is the one
piece of classification information that is still sitting within
each catalog record.
The reason for this is that varieties are quite variable.
There's no real international standards, and
sometimes one
specimen can have
multiple applicable varieties. So it seemed like the catalog was
still the best place to put this.
So to summarize,
I think moving to this relational model for mineral data will
have significant benefits for how we can manage and
interrogate that data.
The ability to link catalog and taxonomy records before
implementing the new fields, as well as
populating most of them quite rapidly
using the open Mindat API once they were available, made the whole
process quite streamlined.
And if anyone is interested in attempting something similar,
especially if you also
use EMu as your collection management system, then I'm very happy to
discuss. So please get in touch
using the email shown there,
and I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.
Hello, everyone. My name is Laura Tilley.
All right. Thank you, Oscar, in absentia.
I believe we have Ben, your talk isn't actually part of the session. Is that right?
We have one more talk. This is going to be Rachel Walcott,
who's going to be talking about... See if I can get her slides up.
Understanding geological specimen use for effective digitization
strategies.
Just make sure.
There you go.
How do I change it?
I think it's just arrows. There's this-
Okay
... but I'm not sure if it... No one's been using it.
So just arrows.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Good morning.
Is this working? Yep, great.
Yes. So today I'll be talking about specimen use
with the grand aim of developing effective digitization
strategies. I have to say we're quite early in the process,
and what I wanted to do in this, there have been other talks on
geological specimen use, but they tended to be more interview based,
and I wanted to get some real hard data about how
collections have been used over time.
And it turns out that there's a number of us that are doing the same thing.
So Adam here, we joined forces when we
started to write the abstract for this, and also Mike Rumsey at the
Natural History Museum of London has also
just started to embark on this. So we've added all our data
together.
Yeah.
I just want to talk a little bit about geological collections.
It turns out that
Yes, maybe people are a bit more familiar with geological collections than I
anticipated, but there are some things about them that are worth
thinking about in terms of how they get used.
Then more general things about use case data sources
and some of the terms and how it relates to geological collections
results, and then
some preliminary digitization priorities from it.
Yeah. So
we're quite late to the game.
And that is partly because geological collections are such a
small part in terms of physical object
numbers of any museum or institution.
And I should mention that what I mean by geological collections
isn't paleontology, because obviously they're much bigger collections.
I'm talking about the abiological collections.
Oops. That was the wrong one. I'll do try that. Yeah. Great.
But even though they're small,
they're diverse. We've heard a lot about rocks, minerals, and a little bit
about meteorites, because those tend to be the dominant
subcollections within a collection.
So we all have
fairly substantial subcollections in our collections.
But depending on the museum, you could be very strong in gems, for example, the
Smithsonian, or very strong in sediments, like ocean
bottom sediments in the Natural History Museum, or any
number of
economic kind of material like ores, or in
our museum, we have hydrocarbons.
But the reason why I've made that mineral bag is not only
because my collection's mostly a mineral collection, but it's just to
emphasize the fact that minerals are objects are
rarely one species. They're a whole family of species,
and each member
of that object can be interesting.
So we have malachite here, but you can see there's at least four other
mineral species, and in fact, there's two stages of malachite on that.
In addition, we have a whole swath of
analytical daughter
samples. Tracing that back to use is going to be a job in
itself.
So this is the structure of the three institutions that have contributed
data,
where we all have substantial mineral collections, substantial rock
collections, and then a whole bunch of other things.
And I've done the percentages here because it will come up later in the
talk.
Yeah. So how do we think about what do we mean by use?
Because most of our collections-- I should say I'm a curator, so I
have this from a curator perspective, not a data scientist perspective.
Oops,
sorry, that's the next slide. But
first thing to talk about is the evidence.
So if you're going to look over a longitudinal study, we have everything from
papers that need to be transcribed.
So I have two volunteers doing that currently at the moment,
looking at our loans collections.
There's inquiry books right up to the present
day data mining, which is Adam's specialty.
Each data set has its biases, and each data set
is really hard to draw the links between them.
But I still think it's a worthwhile
activity to do just to
really have a better understanding of the breadth of
use cases, because we all intuitively know that they're used for many things,
but just documenting that's another matter.
Now, this is the one that I was going to talk about before.
It's just use comes in many forms.
All our collections have specimens in it that had a
use.
It either was
used as a representation of the species or
was in a publication or as an example of a place,
or in terms of rocks, it's often a process, a geological process,
or an expedition or a person. And that often
has quite predicted uses afterwards, like in an exhibition or for
teaching or something like that. But one of the aspects, there's a
couple of use cases that affect
geological
species and objects that are a bit special.
One of them
is
what the Smithsonian has is, and we
do also a little bit, is have minerals with
very stable
well-known chemistry that are used to calibrate analytical equipment, and I
think the Smithsonian sends their minerals right around the world for
that purpose. So that's a constant reuse case
of minerals. But then
there's the new use, and I think in terms of minerals, that is often
the case where it was brought in for one reason, an
example of a pretty rock from Sweden, or that's
probably Greenland actually.
But then it's discovered that it can be used for something completely new,
and in this case, it was how to concentrate heavy, rare elements.
And those are the ones that
we hope our data is ready and accessible for
new use communities.
So now I'll go on to the results of the
three data sets, inquiries, loans, and publications.
And the Smithsonian has a really interesting data set
through their inquiry forms. So they have different
forms for each of those subcollections,
and they're modified for each subcollection
with a range of-
With a range of options, and I've colored
them for the ones that are the classic options, like registration
number or place, which you'll see in the MIDS
system, the Minimum Information for Digital Specimen
system. And that dominates each form, but each form
also has sub-collection specific options as well.
Now, if you look at the frequency of using the
MIDS elements,
Adam provided this plot of
MIDS. It's colored by MIDS elements.
So the most basic elements are low-level MIDS, like
zero and one, and then you have more subject
or discipline, I should say, specific at MIDS three.
And what you can see from this is indeed the most basic terms
are the most popular terms, and the more refined
terms
have lower frequency use, which is what you'd kind of hope.
You'd hope that you're capturing
with the basic elements the most searched-for terms.
But if you start to include those sub-collection
specific options, you really see that there's quite a long tail,
and indeed,
they are often searched for. So
it's worth having them.
Now we go on to loans. These are three plots here
from all three institutions of
the objects that have been useful enough to be loaned out,
per sub-collection.
Well, we have
six decades in Scotland and a couple
decades above.
And to the right, I've also done the relative percentages of
the sub-collections in our institutions.
And
as far as I said early in the project, but what you can get
out of it is that most of our institutions' meteorites are super
sought after. And that'll be because
museums are known to hold them.
And also often the science just uses small samples,
which is important.
Minerals are also
often sought after, but rocks in general, other than the Smithsonian,
tend to be less and less popular
with time.
This is
the results of my volunteers'
work on documenting publications in the
museum.
And I've put at the bottom the loans, so trying to draw this link between loans and
publications.
This is really laborious to do, and I'm sure this plot will
change in my next talk. But what you can see is basically rocks are
less popular, and every geological curator would probably
tell you that, but there it is in
documentation. It also highlights that I haven't been able to, as yet,
find the publications for all those meteorites that we loan out.
So tracing that is a work in hand.
This plot is from the Natural History Museum,
and Mike put together the results of the
purpose of loans for 850 different loaned
material.
To try and understand it, I've colored that sort of in two.
I've done black boxes around what I would call kind of the predicted loans, the
exhibitions, the outreach, the
workshops, that kind of thing, which is about 40% of the
total loan purposes. The red boxes
are many, and that's because, as we all thought, there are many
uses.
I've given some examples on the right there, which relate to
here. It's everything from medical use
to archaeological to material science.
And really, for this community, you should realize very little is
actually for climate change. It is used, but it's a very
small percentage of our total use case.
And finally,
Adam produced this plot. It's
sort of a first pass at, I think it's fair to describe,
of analyzing the publications of
samples from a particular institution.
This case, it's 100 references
from the Smithsonian. And I just think it's potentially a
very powerful way to show the diverse use cases of
geological collections, everything from archeology to new mineral
characterization to formation of the solar system.
This sort of nearest neighbor plot, I hope the next
time-- Oh, I've got five minutes.
Next time we have many more
data for this.
So,
just to wind up fairly
early. First, in terms of specimen use,
I hope we've started to show you that indeed, geological
specimens have very diverse uses.
Some collections are currently more popular than others.
I am interested in seeing how that's changed over time because our collections
are to outlive
our careers. They're there for the long term, so it's worth documenting the long
history of that.
And it's worth noting that there are
relatively few
use
low percentage is used directly for climate change
studies currently. Less than maybe what you would think.
The other digitization takeaways that we have, I think for
the mineral and geoscience community, it's probably
surprising how much images are used.
Someone else has touched upon that.
There's a lot of information in images, but they'll be disappointed to hear that
because it's actually very difficult to take images of
minerals and rock specimens.
The MIDS elements, total,
they're really essential information.
But
we're just starting, and this is the grand aim, is to really
hone down on what those subject-specific terms are.
And one of them, one of the more popular ones, is geological context, and by that
I mean broader, I mean hydrothermal veins.
I mean
pegmatites, not just the
chronostratigraphy,
chronobiosstratigraphy, geostratigraphy,
environmental formation. And this is where the
mineralogical extension for Darwin Core should be able
to help provide
elements for that kind of data in the future.
The end.
All right. We do have time for
questions.
Questions. Do we have any questions? Questions online?
Thank you, Richard.
Yeah, no worries.
So I was late, but I really want to show one thing real quick.
Whoop.
So
this has been a four-year effort of getting more geology, I'm sure. I think Adam...
All right. So Adam gave the presentation earlier about-
You have to talk in the mic. It's great.
Yeah. So about-
Talk in the mic.
Okay, talk to the mic. There we go. All right. So Adam...
What did I do? Yeah.
I should know how to do that.
If you get to these things on time, you know how they work.
Go to the first one, the first presentation.
Zero, zero.
All right. Did you go over this?
I read your notes.
Fantastic. Okay.
We're just going to go to the next one. Thank you all for coming today.
Adam, I'm not going to repeat what Adam already did.
Thank you, Adam, again for doing that. But I want to thank all these people.
So this has been a four-year effort that started with GeoSpecify in
2022, and all of these people and plus many more helped.
And so I really appreciate all of the individuals on the slide.
And for all the dozens of institutions and databases, I have a stack of collection
databases on my computer. People are very happy. Well, they're hesitant.
And I'll tell you something, everybody says the same thing. "My data's not clean.
It's not perfect." I know.
And everyone says that. And then they finally settle down, and they give me their
whole database, which is wonderful, because then I can use it for a lot of things.
And the mineralogy extension is
two, three weeks away, and that covers more than just minerals.
There are terms in there that actually will cover other things like botany, like
hazard type and things like that. And there are terms in there that do cover
other areas of geology. So please check it out. It'll be out very soon.
It just has to be approved by the executive committee. And thanks, everybody.
So I'm on the schedule for discussion.
I also did want to say thanks to everyone for coming.
If I was slightly better on my feet, I would have done a slightly more complete
introduction.
But anyway, I'm Adam Manser. I am the Smithsonian's data manager for the Mineral
Sciences Collection. And I did just want to say that I was really excited to see
this session on the tADWIG schedule,
and all of the efforts that there have been to better integrate geology
collections, and particularly non-paleo geology collections
into the tADWIG universe. It's an exciting time for this.
For those people who are responsible for
non-paleo geo collections, but also paleo geo collections,
there's a couple of things coming down the pike that would be
good to have some additional participation in.
The big one is that the minimal information for a digital specimen
standard is going to be coming up for public review at some point in the near
future.
There is a specific set of rules in that standard for
geology, and it has gone through expert review, but I would think the
group would really value some additional perspectives
on
how those rules are set up.
And so there's big questions about how important
some of the elements are, and we've talked a little about imaging.
How important is imaging
at a systematic level for abiotic geology collections?
And so just getting a better diversity of perspectives on that could be
very helpful.
How much time do we have left in the session?
And
Ben, did you have a plan for discussion?
Where is it? Oh, there we go.
So MIDS, we did add geology at the very end, and there are two
terms that are used in MIDS that are not quite ratified by Darwin Core but
will be once this public review is approved by the execs. That's how new it is.
So there is a whole discipline in elements for geology,
which is really good. So please, if you're interested in that, check it out.
And I think that's about it.
Are there any other questions or comments?
If not, we can-- Why don't we just wrap up early? I'm happy to talk.
I'm here all week. I'm sure Ben and... Oh, looks like Gary.
Yep, and before they all depart, if we could take a quick photo of all
speakers, presenters, and other folks from this session up front.
We'll upload that to the Whova platform as well.
Oh, and yeah. And big thanks to all of our speakers, both in person and
virtual. We really appreciate your taking the time to participate.
This one right here. You can still see it goes out in the stream.
Yeah.
Okay,
good morning, and welcome to the first of the contributed oral
sessions.
I always think that contributed oral sessions are often really, really
interesting because instead of a symposium theme being
suggested, the
themes emerge out of the talks themselves, which
make for really interesting and hopefully
lively sessions of talks today.
So we'll get started. Just a reminder that
any session where you've got me, you're going to get reminded about
putting in an abstract for BIS.
Remember to put in an
extended abstract about your talk, because we would really like to have those
as a permanent record of the conference.
So you've got Ellie and Ellie today co-moderating the session.
That may have been done deliberately.
Ellie
Mario will show each speaker a two minutes to go
sign and a time's up sign, and then we have a hook
in the corner, and if you keep talking after your time's up, then Ellie
will actually physically drag you off stage.
So
with that, I would like to ask our first speaker to come up
to the stage, Yuriy Roskov,
and we will hear about
the Catalogue of Life.
So thank you very much.
There we go.
Thank you.
Good morning, everyone.
So it's already here.
I would like to start
my talk
with a tribute to Frank Bisbee,
remarkable man who was one of the co-founders
of TDWG and also Catalogue of Life founder,
Species 2000 project.
We published
our first edition of the Catalogue of Life in 2001,
and
it included
200,000
species.
Now,
the Catalogue of Life continued as a global checklist or
base release, and through
almost a quarter of a century, we achieved
2.2 million accepted species
in the Catalogue of Life through
entire biota. Definitely, it's not complete yet,
but we are talking about
species not ever described,
neither predicted species,
non-described, but we are talking about species
recognized currently by taxonomists.
We also have extended release. It was publicly
launched this year, and it contributes
over 220,000 species,
mainly in gap areas of the global checklist.
Let me give you a brief introduction to the
global checklist structure. So
Catalog of Life global checklist is an assembly of global
species databases. We use
abbreviation as GSDs.
Those taxonomic checklists curated by expert.
So it's
expert-based knowledge inside those chapters of the
Catalog of Life. Now we have
158 GSDs arranged in management
classification.
We are updating
databases frequently,
and we succeed usually to update two-thirds
of the Catalog of Life every year. Assembly and
management classification
is
scrutinized by Catalog of Life editors.
Here is my imagination for the Catalog of Life.
And
Catalog of Life was planned
as a comprehensive inventory of all valid species known
to biological science globally.
Thanks to Google Gemini,
my old standing idea become possible to
be materialized in the picture in modern days.
Catalog of Life is global and very international project,
and
taxonomists from around the world from different countries
contributed their global checklists in the catalog.
And my apology to other countries which are not
included in my analysis, but members
of our group asked me
to make analysis of
United States contribution to global taxonomy in the
Catalog of Life through
quarter of century,
alongside with
GBIF celebration. So
in my analysis, I included
GSDs curated by experts from the United
States and also international checklists
which are hosted in US-based
software platforms.
At present, US-based
GSDs contribute
820,000
species in the Catalog of Life. It consists 36%
of entire catalog.
This graph showing contribution of US
taxonomists in red to the Catalog of Life.
So right at the beginning
of our project,
we had half of species contributed byITIS
and up to present days, as I said,
it's 36% of the Catalog of Life
contributed by US-based
experts and
databases.ITIS is one of the major
contributors
to the Catalog of Life, right from the beginning.
AndITIS contributes the major global checklist for mammals,
birds, amphibians, arachnids, bees, and many other
taxa.
What is important,ITIS is a principal provider
of global management classification for the Catalog of Life, and
this help us to avoid overlaps in
different checklists and recognize exactly where we
have gaps in global biodiversity.
As of today,ITIS supplies over
158,000
accepted species in the Catalog of Life, and let me acknowledge
Dave Nicholson,
our
long-standing
collaborator,ITIS editor.
The Species Files.
That is another big US contributor.
The project joined the Catalog of Life in 2004
and gradually adding a global checklist for Arthropoda,
Blattoidea, Phasmid, many other groups.
Altogether, we have 12 Species Files checklists
maintained in TaxonWorks software,
and jointly, this checklist supplies over
81,000 accepted species in the Catalog of Life.
And here I would like to acknowledge David Yeates.
He was a
Species Files team founder, benefactor, and also
original software for Species Files.
Then
in addition to Species Files, TaxonWorks software
hosted
set of
other global checklists
which go to the Catalog of Life. These are ScaleNet,
UCD, FreeRAO, Hemarincha, Intimina,
World Catalog of Epiliones, Global Lepidoptera Index, and World
Odonata List. Plus, we have two big
datasets which maintained
In individual software, but
we are processing data through the Catalogue of Life, doing some kind
of validation and then exporting to the Catalogue of Life.
These are Systema Dipterorum and StaffBase.
And let me please acknowledge contribution of Jeff Owen,
Catalogue of Life data manager, and Dmitri Dmitriev,
here in this room.
He is the developer of very important data converters
into TaxonWorks structure. And Matt Yoder,
the lead developer of TaxonWorks exporter to the
Catalogue of Life.
Also, here is the list of independent checklists,
which maintain in different software.
Some of them retired from the Catalogue of Life,
others still staying with us. And let me, in
two minutes, share my dream for global
infrastructure for taxonomic backbone
for biodiversity data.
So my idea is, despite of passing
entire dataset from one
database to another database to aggregators and so on, much
better to organize this as a global unique identifiers
for name or for the record, for name in a nomenclatural
database, for specimens in collection database, for
references in bibliographic database, and then pass to
another aggregator, for example, to taxonomic databases
and change global unique identifier and associated
metadata. And if we pass the same unchanged
global identifier for the name
to taxonomic databases, to the Catalogue of Life, including
assembly in taxonomic concept, then to
GBIF and further on to other aggregators,
and every step will extend metadata
associated with the record. When I shared this idea
with one smart guy, he said, "Well,
it's probably the good idea to use blockchain
technology for this." I cannot judge whether it's true or not,
but every transaction
will be transparent and visible, and only
those
records which were changed in one or another
database
might be updated in aggregators. And
that is very beneficial
for our users to track
data and understand who is the primary provider and what
kind of changes happened in which stage, and
contact appropriate
node in this infrastructure for changes or
improvements of data. But also,
such global infrastructure might be extremely
beneficial for data providers. They will always
keep
control over data quality and data integrity.
If spelling of the name changed in nomenclator, it will
be immediately changed in other places,
taxonomic databases, Catalogue of Life, GBIF, and other
things. Plus,
primary data providers will be able to
see
impact
metrics
of usage of their data. That is important for us as a
scientist. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Yurii.
Now, we do have some time for questions.
We have a question already online from Ian Engelbrecht.
Ian asks, "Are we any closer to a system of universal
identifiers for taxon names?"
You see, it was
a misunderstanding of the idea of global identifiers, unfortunately.
And what we have now,
which are called as global identifiers, we have number
of identifiers. There is no sense to introduce any
kind of global and persistent identifiers if you have
no appropriate infrastructure, which included
all plugged-in
players in this. Yeah. So we are quite far away from
that.
But again, if we really want to have
global infrastructure and if we would like to save our
efforts, energy, and money, we need to build that simple
infrastructure and then give responsibility to
issue global identifier for recognized
nomenclator to registered collection database,
bibliographic database, and other things. It's possible. It's doable.
Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you. Any questions from the floor?
Mitya.
I'll just...
Thank you.
Thank you. This was really good, and I really like the dream part, the closing
part. It's very nice. We had a similar discussion once there was a fire alarm at
Brussels in 2020. At 3:00 a.m., I tried to explain it to
Donald Agosti and Donald Hoburn, was the wrong time of the day.
But what I tried to
say is very similar to what you presented, and I wonder what you think about this.
Any name is a carrier of the meaning, but we don't hyperlink them.
It's a tradition to do it in italics to make it stand alone.
But I think it may be a dangerous statement to make in this room that this
worshiping names
for what they are is actually missing the point that they are the meaning carriers.
Can you imagine the extension of your schema with the purple arrow,
to
see the world where any name mentioned anywhere is actually hyperlinked to
this taxonomic treatment? So that would actually
make it
functional, but I'm not sure how realistic it is. It is probably very far.
Yeah, but I completely agree. Yeah.
Thank you. That was a good, positive answer. Thanks.
It's complicated. That's a good answer. Yeah.
Yeah.
Thank you very much, Yuri.
Yuri, can you go to the back and take your mic off?
Johan, can you, as our third speaker, can you
go and put your mic on? And we will introduce Niels,
who is our second speaker. I'll get your slides up.
Sorry, I'm multitasking.
Where's my mouse? There it is.
Okay.
I would like to acknowledge the
traditional owners of the lands that I work and live.
They are the Wurundjeri and Boonwurrung people of the Kulin
nation, and I would like to
pay my respects to the elders past and present, and I
will extend this to
any traditional owners that are with us today.
What I heard yesterday and the day before at the Living Atlas
work meeting
made me throw out my
admittedly poorly prepared talk.
So I'll come to ad lib
a little bit.
Cam's talk yesterday was actually a
perfect
introduction of my talk.
And,
yeah. So I think the problems that
came with experience with using these checklists
is a data quality issue, and I'm quite convinced
that we can fix this and that it's actually
not all that hard. So
that's my bold statement right at the beginning.
So I've got the conclusion out of the way.
So TCS, the standard for taxon data,
was
ratified
last December,
and
yeah,
was a bit anticlimactic and apparently didn't even
merit a mention in yesterday's
opening statement, but it happened.
I'm not
naive enough to think that once the standard is there, people will start
using it.
So I think we need reference
implementations, and I've got this flora,
which is sort of my canvas and needed to be upgraded
anyway, so I started to
work on a
data model for that
flora and
yeah, I'm going to show you now. So what I did is,
divide all the different resources that I needed.
So we already have the flora, so I knew which resources they were,
and
yeah, divided them into
what I called layers. And I thought that was just
because,
I'm a systematist, so I like to pigeonhole things.
But my new best friend, Google Gemini,
suggested what I was doing was actually
separation of concerns.
So sounds much better. The knowledge organization system, that's also
something that Google Gemini came up with.
I would have come up with something quite less grandiose.
So I'll just go through the model very quickly.
Is that the Enter button? Yep.
So this is my model. It's actually one layer.
So it's the layer there's the taxon concept in, which is central
to
TCS, and it also should be central to any
taxon
system.
And so
I've called that the taxon concept resource.
Well, the layer that the taxon concept is in, I called that the semantics
layer. And
so
taxon concept are scientific hypotheses.
Basically, that's where the science is sitting.
And then, the next layer where all the names are sitting
are called
the syntax layer.
And so the names are sitting there, typification, name relations, name
usage,
all sort of stuff. And I
can't really take credit for it myself, so David Remsen
wrote an article in which he separated syntax
or syntactics, what we call it, from semantics.
When I looked it back up, I thought that he made a distinction quite
different from what I did, but it's the fact that he made the distinction that's
important,
I think. So the next layer-
Oh, I turned it around. It's authority, so
that includes the provenance and the
attribution, so references and agents,
links to pretty much any other layer. Well, not pretty much, any other layer.
Next one is governance, which
maintain a taxon tree. So there's a taxon tree and a taxon tree
node, and I've got taxon tree revisions sitting in there.
And then finally, we've got a narrative layer, and that's
your profile sitting and everything else.
It looks really small, but it's actually where most of our flora is sitting.
Then we have a
couple of different layers that
are not really part of the model, but we need to
make
flora work or system work. So the
identity layer,
which has our external identifiers, so IPNI
identifiers, Tropicals identifiers for me, I'm a
biologist,
MicroBank identifiers, orchids go there,
IPNI standard form for authors.
Infrastructure, which has users,
controlled vocabularies, and audit log, things like that.
And then
extension, which has distribution,
occurrences, keys,
glossary,
et cetera. And it's actually not very clear.
It depends on your application, what an extension is and what a narrative is.
So
some stuff that I had in extension have now moved
back into narrative, like the distribution.
Yeah, so I've got
system, just like to classify stuff.
So
apart from the main domain
entities like taxon concept, taxon name, agent
reference, et cetera,
we've got,
I think,
by sidecar pattern,
and with
different types of sidecar patterns.
So one is extension, so we've got that for a taxon name.
So things like scientific name, vernacular name, taxon
concept label, hybrid formula, informal name.
That's also all not standardized, so you can do what you would need for your
application.
And same for the reference, which you don't call reference type because they're
already there, but I've got them reference roles and the things
like treatment.
What is it?
Treatment version, taxonomy, protologue, typification,
that sort of stuff.
And,
so you know what the reference is used for.
Also,
some of them have
extra properties
or extra fields,
but other of them are just semantic flags.
And then we've got another--
This is actually the more important sidecar pattern, so this is more like a
functional
sidecar pattern. So we've got the taxon concept, like a main
entity, and then we've got the taxon tree node.
So that's the taxonomic position of a taxon concept in
a tree
or in a classification. And then
we've got the profile and that's
the profile, that's the Copiapinoe group, basically.
And,
yeah, so the importance,
what it does is
having the extensions allows us to keep the taxon concept
immutable,
which is a very nice property to have for
any entity, but
especially taxon concept,
because this is about taxon concept.
And,
so then we've got other things. We've got associated entities and
maps, which are
structures that
connect
different
main entities to each other. So, we've got the
nomenclatural types,
which links a name to a specimen or a name to another name.
And we've got the taxon concept mapping, which
connect taxon to
taxon as a
mapping. And then we also have maps,
which
your name usages and your relationship, they just map to each other.
They're not entities by themselves.
So you use them in tabular data, or you can use them in tabular data, but you don't
want to see them in RDF or JSON, or you don't want to
have them identifiers.
So the phylogeny extension,
I made that as I got a phylogeny tree and
a phylogenetic tree, phylogenetic tree node, operates taxon review.
Therefore, a phylogeny can't really be an extension.
It has to be the core, because that's actually the semantics of our domain
sitting there. So then I realized it actually only had the
infrastructure, so I added this
thing. I'm not going to spend too much time on it.
It's something that I still want to implement.
And so these are the references for the final reference.
And so if we go
back to that model, and then we see that the
semantics and
syntax are covered
by TCS, and narrative will be covered
by Plinian core, authority is covered by Darwin Core, and
governance is not covered by anything.
Part of TCS, we covered movedRank and the parent in
there.
And
when I said that the profile looks so small, but it's actually almost
everything. So that reminded me of the Darwin Core
conceptual model, where the taxon
looks so small. It actually
does a lot. And I think that's actually the problem with the Darwin
Core taxon, because you try to shoehorn an entire domain into a
single entity. And
now,
since we got the standard, now the
TCS maintenance group looking for other stuff to do,
new things to do, how we're going to maintain it, now we're going to proselytize
it.
So when we're done basking in our glory,
I think a logical step would also be making a
conceptual model for TCS or for taxon data.
So that's what
I think the direction we should be going,
and then work with the Darwin Core maintenance group to work on the interfaces
between the two models,
and then we've got the whole system.
And so I want to reiterate what I said in the introduction.
The problem with the taxon data, they're definitely
fixable if
you take care of our
semantic blind spots, our
conceptual blind spots, and
make the right infrastructure or the right systems for it.
That's it. Thank you very much. I got some references then.
Thank you.
Thanks, Niels. Again, we have a question online
from Dima.
Niels, I wonder how do you see organization of
alternative taxon concepts?
Alternative taxon concepts?
Yeah.
That's all he's written.
I think it should be alternative taxonomies,
probably, but that's all what the taxon concept is about because
the meaning is not in the name, it's in the taxon concept.
So
by having these taxon concepts,
you can actually deal with
the diversity in taxonomic views, let me say it
like that. So conflicting taxon concept, but also
different versions
of the same taxonomy.
Any questions in the room? Cam.
Oh, sorry, I have to run over, and then Yuri.
Is it on?
Yeah, it is.
Sorry, Adeline.
Hi, Niels. Thanks. That was fantastic.
I do have a question. I noticed the really elegant way that
you had-
Sorry?
Oh, can you hear me?
Yeah, I just didn't hear that last bit.
Yes, I can. Just a bit.
Yep.
Sorry. I really like the
idea. I'm just curious, you had hybrids as a
very elegant kind of side module. How would you go about handling,
say, species integrades or complexes?
It was Hybrid Formula, which is for the names.
Ah, right. Okay.
And
so,
how I would deal with
species aggregates?
That's more for me as a taxonomist.
And
yeah, it's difficult.
Okay, last question from Yuri.
Thank you. Niels, thank you very much for your work and for your presentation.
So when I'm thinking about definition of
taxonomic concepts,
what is defined taxonomic concept?
The simple answer, the set of specimens which
included by the author of the concept
under ID, the scientific name. Type is the anchor for the
name, but set of specimens selected by the
author of the concept
define the concept. So the same question about hybrids.
So how you are treating hybrids. If you have overlapping
subsets of specimens, and some
specimens
set in between two different concepts, they
are hybrids or named as hybrids. We need genetic
confirmation of this, of course. But yeah, so that's my opinion.
Set of specimens included in the concept.
That is the base.
Well, that's more like circumscription.
So what were you trying to-
It's a just a comment.
It's a comment.
Yeah, okay. I don't have to say anything.
I didn't quite understand, so we'll talk.
Yes.
Excellent. Thank you very much, Nils.
Nils, can you take your microphone off?
And Clara, I think you are next after Johan.
So could you
jump up and put a microphone on?
And the next... So sorry, Johan. I'll get...
And we welcome our next speaker
to the stage. Welcome, Johan.
Thank you.
So we're moving
from
the more larger
scene to a national example here in
Sweden.
So we have,
I think I have it on the next slide,
Artportalen, our citizen observatory,
now 26 years and going strong.
And in 2004, we introduced our taxonomic
database, which is more of a practical.
It's not extensive, every name. It's more what's needed
for use in
Swedish conservation, you could say,
management.
So that was started in 2004, and
that uses identifiers for
taxon concepts. And by that, I mean in the same way as Nils here,
not regarding the name really, just the idea.
So that is tied to the taxon idea. So
everything needs a taxon ID and at
least one recommended scientific name in the database.
But then the name can change, and
the taxon ID stays
stable to that concept. But then, of course, things can happen.
We can revisions and you merge things because they were the same
thing, and
so they're not really stable in that way, but it's
least traceable, so you can
automatically, I guess, find what happened.
So that's the traceable thing there,
even if things are no longer accepted, so to speak.
So
I used to work with this database, but now I manage our citizen
observatory, Artportalen, instead.
And so it's quite fitting that I manage when
they
manage the taxonomy, which is
actually published whenever they want during the
every day, so that they publish it, and then we actually
aggregate it every night. And then there is a, I think it's a Darwin
Core file, actually, they use
to update both our
system that harvests other databases, but also Artportalen.
And then we also update
Artportalen every second month because we want to
manage the changes, so we don't want to do that every day or
every week.
Because we also then manage a little news
flash about this, what happened, so that works for the database as well.
Even though we actually don't incorporate everything.
We don't want everything in the taxonomic database to be
possible to report, so there's a
filter there as well.
But whenever name changes, that's simple because it's
still the same taxon ID, and the observations are tied to the
same thing.
And lumps are
also, well, now it's been replaced by another taxon
ID, so you just move observations to that new
or changed, actually, the observation ID, taxon
ID.
Splits can be a bit
more complicated, but
basically, you would keep the observation on the
original taxon, that which it's now represented by
maybe two species or three as what we call a collective
taxon in the database then.
And then we have new taxon IDs for the separate
species. But if we don't have any information, we just keep it on the
collective taxon, which is still in the system, and you can still
do reports on it. Maybe it's impossible to
know. There are three fungi look the same.
That's why everyone thought it was just one species.
But if we have more information than this, then we can, maybe
only one of these species occur in Sweden, so the other is in continental
Europe, or then we can just move them to that one instead.
And this is where we're not really fully automated
because there's not that many cases every two months,
even if we have,
I think it's something like
a million records every two months, about.
But
the changes in the taxonomy are not that many.
So it's kind of
better to look at things, to be pragmatic still, but you
can see the possibilities for at least have
routines, or maybe you can standardize these things if you have
identifiers to the taxa.
So
within the country, maybe you have one species on an island and the
other on the mainland, or north and south, or they have
different chronology population or species in spring and
other in
Fall.
And you can also inform the users that none of this happened,
and you maybe know
because you have more information. You can put it on one of these two species.
You could read maybe a paper that
was published about that.
But then there are actually more complications because maybe
a species was lumped into B that turns out was
lumped into C. So we have to sort of take care of,
look further, not stop at the first step.
Or sometimes we have,
for example, plants. People in Sweden want to
see a lot of plants, so they try to, "Oh, now this has escaped from the
garden. I can make an
observation." And now they plan to my list there.
But sometimes
we allow that, it's included in Artportalen, but
someone actually later looks even closer.
No, that was not that species, so we exclude it again.
And then we have to move this observation to something else.
So either we know what it was, or we maybe move it up to a genus level.
So it's kind of a bit you have to look into these
cases.
Or if you have
taxon concept which are totally revised, you can't really
point to one
single
station where it moves. So then we have to
figure out what to do with those, but there is no single taxon ID
to move it to.
Yeah, and it was erroneously recorded as occurring in Sweden there.
We also have
these taxa which are in the taxonomic database.
So they can be excluded for other reasons as well.
I think I had a case where
the referrer was to a concept which was no longer
accepted, but it was in the database.
But we keep everything
so it's traceable.
But that's actually about what I want to talk, so I'll just
acknowledge Johan Nilsson who founded Artportalen, and
Oscar Tjernvall who founded our taxonomic database.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions from the floor? Yeah. Oh, hang on. Sorry.
You can go running.
Hi. Thanks for sharing the very interesting details. That's very useful.
A few,
two questions that came to mind. So do you mean that you actually
scanned every occurrence once you have a taxon update
to
either decide it can be automatically
changed to a new taxon ID or you have to-
Yeah
... you scan all the concurrences?
Yeah. IT guys looks what has changed since the
last date-
Mm-hmm
... during these two months, and then sees what taxa are
involved, what are new taxa.
Name changes are simple, but
maybe some things are excluded or they have changed
category to something that needs to be addressed.
So it
might be,
want to say,
100 new taxa each two month and
maybe
10, 15 that needs to be changed to new taxon ID.
But often they ask me, even if it actually says what it's
changed to, they want to be sure, so they ask me to
have a look at things anyway. And
we have
people who take care of different organism groups, so we
send an email to them if they know anything special as well to check
for this list because it's not that long.
So it's manageable for a country like Sweden.
I think we have about 60,000 species in the database, and
not all are in Artportalen, but I think we have
observations of about 40,000 of those.
Okay. Thank you. And the second question is, so you keep track of all
the changes of the taxon ID on every occurrence?
Yeah.
The taxon ID changes is of course in the
taxonomic database. That's traceable.
You can look at the history for each taxon and what happened to it.
And
then we sort of introduce that to the-
Observatory
... citizen observatory.
Okay.
I think we could probably log more of that information.
For example, I don't think the model
doesn't include which name the observer used when
he did the original report, which will be useful to
actually interpret what they thought it was
rather than what the name it is nowadays.
So there are some improvements there.
But we're building a new version with modern technology.
This was launched in 2014, and yeah, that's old
technology. It wasn't even built for smartphones or so.
Okay. Great. Thank you.
Okay.
Excellent. Thank you very much, Johan.
Thank you.
You can take your mic off.
Piotr, can you keep your mic on?
Okay, we have a
comment
which I'll ask as a question just while
I'm changing over the slides.
Does anyone know
why Systema Dipterorum might be down at the moment?
No, but I can ask somebody to fix this.
Okay.
Okay. So the next speaker I would like to invite up to the stage is
Clara to talk again to us about Brazil.
I need to-- Okay, now it's working, right? Yeah.
So good morning. It's my last talk.
So I'm going to talk about modernizing Brazil's taxonomic backbone, how
Checklist Bank supports biodiversity and genetic heritage systems.
In Brazil, we have two major-- Well, I'm a data manager
in the GBIF Brazil. I'm also part of technical--
I'm also part of GBIF and also now recently
OBIS Node as well. We are such a small team,
so we work in everything. But we are
lucky we have people that support us in different ways, like
Australia with infrastructure, Camila with Checklist Bank, and
all the people. So
we are two, but we are receiving lots of help.
Not
sure what's...
Okay.
Let me see. No. So Brazil is the most
biodiverse country in the world. We have
120,000 animal species, more or
less
67,000 plants. So at the end,
it's almost
180,000 species. So we deal with lots of
biodiversity, and Brazil cares about biodiversity.
We have
two important
lists. So not all the countries have their own national
taxonomic data. I would say Australia has, Mexico has,
Brazil has, New Zealand, not all the countries, but we
have. So we have two important
lists. They are not a list, they are catalogs because we
update it monthly. So we have the Flora and Flora of
Brazil and the Brazilian Taxonomic Catalog of Fauna.
At the national level, we have also Protax.
It's a program to train taxonomists.
So, I think every two years there's
a launch of this program, and people receive scholarships to
work with taxonomy.
And then we have a new idea of having the Brazilian
Catalog of Life.
It's to merge these two,
flora and
fauna, and also fossils and microorganisms.
It's a 10 years project,
and so the idea will be to merge all this
information, all these catalogs, and then we have the Brazilian
system.
These are the
flora and fauna catalog. So
this was launched in 2010. There are more than
700 taxonomies and specialists updating
taxonomy on a monthly basis. We
have all these catalogs integrated directly with the IPT.
We have four extensions in this list, and then we
publish in GBIF and also in the World Flora Online.
So this is for the plants. So it was
163,000, but it
maybe changed.
And we have the fauna as well, same infrastructure,
but it's a little bit more recent. 2015 it was launched,
more than 800 zoologies and taxonomies
also integrated with all the IPT and
also in GBIF.
So what we do with all this information, so
we have in Brazil three important systems.
This is the national system for management of genetic heritage and
associated traditional knowledge. This is law.
So all research that you do
with biodiversity, you must
put it here. You need to register. It's not well
implemented, but if you use some
species with traditional knowledge, you develop a product, and this is
not registered, you will receive a fine of that.
And so we have
our GBIF
national portal, and this is like a
system that when you go to a protected area, you have to
register
what you are doing and send the data to them.
So
these three systems must use the same taxonomy.
It doesn't make any sense each one uses a different taxonomy.
So what we do?
For that system, microbiology is included.
and we don't have it as a
Brazilian list, so we
need to use Catalog of Life to
fulfill or to complement our
data. So we have the taxonomic catalog, the flora
and the funga, and then we mix it in Checklist Bank.
We use Checklist Bank to clean the data, to merge the data,
and to add new other groups.
like
microorganism, and then we download the Darwin Core Archive,
and then we use this same Darwin Core Archive.
Here we don't use microorganism because we'll be really high and then
it doesn't make any sense.
And then when we have the Checklist Bank, we download the Darwin Core Archive
here with micro, here without, and the other one
just without as well.
So
once it's all in Checklist Bank, we use the
Living Atlas infrastructure with the taxonomy as the most important thing.
So the Darwin Core Archive
from Checklist Bank, we index in Living Atlas
Brazil, and then we process all the information,
images, multimedia layers, species profile, and records.
It's all depending on this taxonomy.
That's really important because in Living Atlas, they process
the taxonomy. So here up we will see the original name
versus the process name. So it is possible
if all
data sets are not updated in taxonomy,
Living Atlas will process the taxonomy.
So here. We will see the original value
here and the process value
that follows the official taxonomy.
That's really important for public policies.
These are the NEO 30. Oops,
sorry.
The 30 targets. So it's important to deal properly
with the taxonomy because the number 20 and
21, it targets directly with data, so
we need to
have our taxonomy. Oops, sorry. I don't know what's going on here.
Okay. So we also as
we use the taxonomy link with the occurrences, we also
develop maps of how we know our taxonomy,
our data our biodiversity in Brazil.
Here, for example, in yellow is where we know
what's going on with our biodiversity, but as we see, we
still have lots to know in Brazil. We only know
a little bit the coast of Rio and São Paulo, but
we don't have any information about marine
data, and also in Amazonia, we don't have enough data to
do some public policies.
So the role of Checklist Bank. Checklist Bank is helping us in
so many ways.
First,
we
use
Checklist Bank to clean our two
lists.
Sorry.
Okay. So
we use Checklist Bank to--
I don't know what to do here.
Is it this cable that you need?
Yeah.
Which one? Here?
No, the thing that's causing the image to disappear.
Which?
It's here.
So it's that.
No, I would say.
Continue.
Okay. Thank you.
So we clean
the
two lists. We had duplicates. We are not
organizing. We don't use the correct names
sometimes in Darwin Core. Sometimes it's in Portuguese, and we have some
misunderstandings. And then once it's clean, we create a
few projects to manage. So for example, for the Brazilian
taxonomy, we do some merging here.
We merge the list of flora and fauna.
Also, we put the invasive species because sometimes we will have
occurrence related with the invasive species.
We also
create a few projects about mixing.
We do the list of microorganism of Catalog of Life, and then we produce
a Darwin Core archive as well. And sometimes our fungi list is
not enough, so we need to complement
with GBIF
fungi list. So then we export everything
to Darwin Core Archive, and then we use in CBR and
other systems.
We also republish this data again in the IPT.
We assign some DOIs as well
to keep the
different versions to know what's
going on with the taxonomy. So we
assign the DOI at the IPT level, so
we republish again. We don't send it to any
other system because it's going to be duplicate, but we keep it here with our
DOI.
And to finish next steps, we realized that Darwin Core
Archive maybe won't be enough in long term.
We will need to implement CalDP, at least not for
the Brazilian
system, but for the other heritage, other system, we will
need to track
what happened with a term. So
taxon IDs, we
need
better
taxon ID management, and we will need soon
include a- In the species list, what species has
some traditional knowledge related and which ones
don't have, and we will try to manage and
integrate other type of checklists soon in our
big taxonomy. So that's it. Thank you so much.
Okay, any questions for Clara?
Piotr?
You have the mic.
Should I-- Okay.
Does your system allow you to,
assess, estimate the number of
species in the country? Because I'm sure it's not so low
as you presented it now. It must be much more species in
Brazil than-
So that they are not described?
No. But yeah, maybe that.
Oh, phew.
And the sub-question is whether you registered all
the species documented, recorded from Brazil in your
system.
So we are not mapping what's happening.
So when some species
discover, they publish in an article, and then
this person has to
ask for a login in the
catalogs and add the species. Sometimes we're
not having money to maintain these two catalogs,
so
there is a gap between when species discover and when is in
the system. And sometimes when we have endangered,
threatened species
list published in
an official
journal,
sometimes when we publish the list,
we recognize that a few taxa are not already in the catalog,
so we send a message to say, "Okay, these two species must be
registered in a catalog." So
we need to establish better flows for that.
Donat.
So quite a few were--
Can you hear me?
I can hear you.
It's okay, keep talking.
Huh?
It should be on.
Can you hear me now? Okay. So
quite a few species, new species especially, are discovered through our
channel. So when they're published, we extract
from publication the new species, we send to the checklist
bank, to GBIF. And are you actually using this or?
No.
But we will.
The problem is when you discover a
species, you publish in Zoo Keys, in Phyto Keys, and this kind,
and then they publish the data in GBIF,
and we don't have these mechanisms to check
and
put it in the national list.
Oh, we could help you to do it then.
Yeah. Even sometimes
the
researchers from Brazil that publish this information, they don't know that
this data will be in GBIF soon.
Yep. Okay. I think that's fabulous, Clara.
Thank you.
Thank you. You can take your microphone off.
Juny, you can get a microphone on, and
I will just...
It's not working.
I wouldn't use that. I think that's
seems to be a problem.
I keep losing the mouse.
There we go. That should work.
Okay.
Yeah.
That's good.
Let's hope.
Let's hope the HDMI cable behaves.
Okay. Sorry. Piotr.
Yep.
To talk about Poland. Moving countries.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Piotr Piekarski. I'm a node manager and
head of delegation.
I play both these roles, and
as an entomologist, I was
always very aware of the
complexities and intricacies of taxonomy.
And
I'm going to show you
our new tool, new device, new database system
allowing us to control our national checklists.
And
for many years,
I was complaining how badly organized is
the information available about species in our country.
And thanks to the recent
projects and
subsidies from the government, our successes in
obtaining them, we
were able to develop our skills and our capacities in
this respect.
So this is the part of the Polish GBIF's node
implementation.
The project
was set, this is information which is missing, was
launched actually in 2021, but only now we
are achieve the zero level to allowing
users to
edit the checklists online.
The project was
based on the work of more than
cooperators, specialists from more than 20 institutions.
Everything was done, conducted under the umbrella
of the Polish Biodiversity Information Network, SIBP.
The address you have on the QR code.
And
all the checklists were published as checklist dataset through GBIF.
Well, they are automatically synchronized with Checklist
Bank, of course, but we want to develop
the organization of
what is available in Checklist Bank using their
management system.
And we hope to be
mapped by the governmental institutions and
agencies in the future.
The
scope of the
database covers all eukaryotic and cyanobacteria species
recorded for Poland. It turned out it's more than
expected. It's more than
65,000 species.
All checklists were divided into 107 chapters.
The authors are supervising
the composition of the checklists.
Every species is documented by at least one
bibliographical reference,
so we also keep a bibliography here.
Every species has assigned status, whether it is present or
not, or
it demands confirmation,
so it has a question mark then.
Keywords and attributes are also comprised
in the database, so
species are connected with some kind of system of keywords and
keys and values associated.
The reference can be a publication of an expert
opinion,
and the taxonomy tables were based on the ITIS data model,
published recently, some years ago.
And the
authors control the list
and the way they are presented.
The digital catalog of
biodiversity of Poland is maintained on
our data portal,
our own solution for management of
the database.
And
this is also managed by the authors through the tools
dedicated for users to
give them possibility to control the
taxonomy itself and the composition of
the checklist, and of course, it's regulated by the system of roles and
permissions.
So
only some people can
have the privileges to do the job.
I'm going to show you a number of slides
just to illustrate how it works. So
here we see the main
view of the portal.
It's divided into a number of so-called perspectives, and the last
perspective is about checklists, so here is the list of checklists available,
covering the biodiversity of the country.
And each record here is
published in GBIF, and this represents
individual
checklist chapters. So here we have some
springtails and proturans
showed, and the right panel shows you the structure of
the checklist. So it's quite simple, straightforward.
You can
extend the list.
You can download it
as a Excel sheet.
So
you can also
show the details and the
publications connected with each record,
like showing
a
proof that the
species is present in Poland.
And the
references
are included in our database, so you can use the
details instead of seeing the
simple abbreviated
references. You can
extend them, and you can see the details of them
also. So
this is the way each chapter is presented in GBIF
website. Here is the same on the Checklist Bank
portal.
And we have an additional way to present the
whole, so this is like a summary of all
taxa, with numbers representing the number of species
recorded for Poland for this particular
taxon group, and of course, it's
maintained in the taxonomical database.
So we have also the additional graphical panel to show
it in more comprehensive and attractive
way. So here is the whole, with the
tooltips showing the
numbers for each particular
part. And it is interacting with the left side.
So if you click here, the right
panel will change, and
actually you can
filter it also here.
You can also control the way you show the structure of
the list. So you can look at
different levels depending on the user's needs.
Now
all
levels are checked, so it is very detailed.
And also you can control to some extent the
depth of the graph on the right side.
So here it's a
medium. Here is more wide solution, so it
may seem to be not very complete because some of
the levels are not
represented for
all the groups.
And here is the narrow
view. So it is
less complicated, less
levels are
shown.
And a
click was done here, so the list is filtered on the left side.
And
here is again the
wider
view chosen.
And
here you can see the details of the checklist
on the right side. So
then it filters all hexapods, and all hexapods
filter is used on the right side.
Sorry. You can
also click the details of the taxon and
go to the first
perspective, first view, first panel showing the taxonomy tree.
And if you choose
the gallery and pictures, then it
will be possible to filter it and
select the level
of the taxonomical groups
you choose and
use it as a browser to browse through different
groups of
taxa.
Users can edit it,
play with taxonomy, play with the structure of the checklist.
And we plan to extend the checklist with
DNA barcodes.
We think about
transforming the database to a
series of publications covering the whole diversity of the country.
I'm jealous to Norwegians for them to
have this kind of publication. For Poland, it was not possible before.
And the good idea would be, I
had something like this in my mind, to propose such
an
integrated
approach.
Creating national checklists in Europe to
compare the biodiversity levels of different countries.
It's possible, it's doable. It could be a good
idea for the nodes
for the cooperation.
So thank you very much.
Okay, we don't have any questions online at the moment, but do we have questions in
the room?
You've done such a good job, Piotr.
Thank you.
Okay. And
so we're moving countries again for our last talk.
We're going to Taiwan this time.
This talk is
a little jewel
to add to the end of the session about taxonomy, and it will
address a slightly different topic.
But I will just bring up the slides
and invite
Chun-I to come and tell us all about
Taiwan.
Hello, my name's Chun-I Chiang. I'm from Taipei.
Today, I'm going to talk about our national biodiversity
information action campaign. I will share
a story of how we made the five years plan in
Taiwan.
Although this presentation focuses on biodiversity
information infrastructure at the national level,
taxonomy is an important foundation for making biodiversity
data interoperable, connected, and
reusable across organizations.
Okay. So let's look at how our
plan changed over time. From 2021 to 2025,
our goal was to build the basic system.
We worked on basic database exchange and finding
talent. Another important lesson from this phase was
the connected biodiversity databases requires not
only data exchange mechanisms, but also should take
taxonomic references. Now, for the next five
years, from 2026 to 2030,
we want to make the system stronger.
We will focus on open data, database integration, and
building a network.
After five years of building the system, we also learned
that building the infrastructure is only the first step.
The next challenge is how to keep the system working and
growing over time. The 2026 to 2030
campaign builds on the infrastructure and partnerships
established during 2021 to 2025, but
shifts the focus from establishment to long-term
resilience.
There are two copies of the 2022
to 2030 campaign, so please feel free to have a
look at the presentation.
Okay.
How did we deliver the 2022 to
2030 campaign? We followed the four simple
steps. First, review. We looked back at our
past five years. And second, identify.
We found our current problems and new needs.
Third, co-develop. This is very important.
We formed a small working group of 10 people from different
research and collection institutes.
We had a two-day workshop to map out the data
flow in Taiwan's informatics system.
Fourth, formulate. After the workshop, we held nine
online meetings to finalize the details.
Finally, we wrote our new action campaign.
Working together helped us develop
practical solutions.
And we learned three main things from this process.
First, cross-domain collaboration is valuable.
It helps us make sure that our strategy responds to
real needs. Second,
coordination takes time. Working with different agencies
requires a lot of time and effort. Third, we face
capacity constraints. People are very busy.
Participants have their own daily responsibilities, so they
have limited time to additional tasks.
We therefore need to plan carefully.
During our review, we asked what makes our system
vulnerable? We found four big challenges.
Number one, governance. It is hard to coordinate between
different agencies.
Number two, data flow. We have data, but it does
not always exchange easily.
Number three, monitoring. It is a gap between having
data and actually using it for long-term monitoring.
Number four, sustainability. To keep the system running,
we need stable funding and people with the capacity to maintain
it. To fix these problems, we need a resilient
system.
To solve challenges, our campaign has five
strategic directions. First, system
interoperability.
For biodiversity information to calculate across
institutions, we need not only APIs,
but also shared taxonomic references.
Taxonomy checklist provide a common language that allows
datasets from different organizations to be connected and
reused.
Second, data openness and quality.
We want better data standards. Third,
network sustainability. We want public-private
collaboration and stable funding.
Fourth, inter-agency collaboration.
We will share more technology between departments.
Finally, data usability. We want to make data
easy to use and cite. Together, these directions make
our system more resilient.
Now, how do we turn strategy into action?
Let's look at our 2025 data gaps in
year.
Our big goal was
to find and fill the blind spots in Taiwan's biodiversity
data. How did we do it? Before, we mapped the
data to see where data was missing.
These gaps can occur across geographic, temporal, and
taxonomic dimensions.
Then we mobilized our TBRE partner to help.
Finally, through collective action, our partner
provided data to fill those empty spaces.
This shows our campaign in action.
By being open and working together, we can really improve our
data.
Here are our achievements from this gap-filling action.
We actually filled
852 map grid cells. We added
over
3.8 million records. This includes many
protected and rare species. You can also
see the coverage rate
for different groups. For example, mosses in
2025 are over 57%.
Annual change between 2024 is
4.33 percentage points.
You can scan the QR code on the screen to see the
full dashboard on our website.
As we look to the future, we ask a big question: What
makes a biodiversity data system truly resilient?
We are still learning, and we focus on three things.
First, governance. How can cross-sector
collaboration remain active over time?
Second, data and technology. What are the best
ways to keep data flowing and high quality?
Interoperability also depends on shared taxonomic
references. We need to keep these references updated
as the data landscape changes.
Third, sustainability. How do we get long-term
financial support? For us, resilience means not only
keeping the infrastructure running, but also
keep it connected, useful, and able to adapt to new
needs. We hope to learn from all of you here today.
Finally, I want to say a big thank you to all our partner
units. This work is only possible because of the Taiwan
Biodiversity Information Alliance.
Thank you very much for listening.
And for the Q&A, my colleague, AKA my
translation robot, Jerome, will join me and help
me answer the questions.
Excellent. Thank you very much.
Do we have any questions
from the floor?
I have one.
Excellent.
So one of the things you mentioned was the bureaucratic
issues when you are trying to have a project that is lasting multiple years and
on the long term. And
I think everybody in the room is
struggling with this in a way or another.
So do you have any idea
what ideas do you have to
deal with this? Because it's an issue for literally everybody, especially in the
context of taxonomic cataloging and stuff like this where it's easy to get money
to start a project, but it gets really complicated to maintain stuff in the long
term.
Okay. Thank you for your question.
So actually,
for our case, it's like previously, this alliance is really
just a
signed MOU between different government institutes.
So there's no real organization running that thing.
So what we are coming through now is trying to shift
from a non-formal organization into a real
organization to be able to receive funds.
But, one way maybe at responding to your
question is the reason we want to change into a
non-governmental
organization is we may start to have
these
participant fees from these different government institutes.
So
every year, they will have to pay for the fees.
We have now 16 government institutions in the
alliance. So if they can each share a bit, then maybe it's easier to have
this long-term infrastructure running.
Yeah.
Excellent. Thank you. Any more questions?
Cam.
Oh.
Thank you for the talk. It was really interesting.
You mentioned
trying to look at gaps from a
taxonomic,
spatial and,
the other one that I always forget, temporal. Thank you.
We're trying to do the same thing. I'm very interested in
how you're approaching that methodologically to identify
gaps.
Thank you for the question.
I think actually we did it in a very straightforward way.
So, it's just like previously these data are scattered, and now we
finally can put it all together from different government institute.
So it's
almost as straightforward as the visualization plots we see on
Jupyter. So the maps and the temporal
accumulation of data, and also
mapping the current
species that have occurrences to the taxonomic, to the species
catalog of Taiwan to see,
for example, we also have around 60,000 species
that was logged on the catalog
of life in Taiwan. But maybe we only have around 30,000
species that have occurrence data.
So just like this, mentioning that there's more than the half
that still means we know they exist, but we don't even have any open
data in the database, and that's one thing.
Oh, and also for the spatial part, I
think it's also similar elsewhere is that we
gridded the data into--
We
put all the data into different grids, like five-kilometer grids,
and in that way, we will also put a standard on
these data, these grids, which
grids has only less than 1,000 occurrence data.
And at least we can put more efforts into those grids that
doesn't have enough data yet. And we share this information to
our participants, and because they come from different
backgrounds, some focus on water conservation, some
focuses on national parks, and then they can pick their choice on
which grid they are going to spend their new resource on the
survey projects.
Okay. Thank you. I think we're pretty much out of time, and so it's
lunchtime now. Now, lunchtime, if anyone has the-
app open. We've just changed the venue because it was showing as being down in
the foyer where we had the break. It's not actually in the foyer where we had the
break. It's actually
up the stairs to the third floor in the restaurant.
So the easiest way straight from here is to go through that door at
the back and cut across
Room B, because hopefully they will be finished.
Cut across Room B, and then you'll see a door with some stairs leading up.
There is also an elevator if you would prefer to take that.
Otherwise, you can, if you wish to get extra exercise, go all the way back
down the stairs, across the foyer, back up the stairs, and that way.
So just in case you haven't had enough steps today, then you can
do it that way.
So
thank you very much for your participation in this session.
Please join me in thanking all of our speakers.
Sorry about that.
No, you're fine.
The screen was here.
I don't know how to make this go full screen.
Oh, wait.
Maybe here.
Sorry, I don't have cards to flash up, so if you could give them a hand signal.
Yeah.
10 minutes. We've got 10 minutes, 20 to go.
Can you get us-
Let's get started. Sorry, I had to close the door
to remove Deb,
so we weren't having competing myself and Deb. Okay.
Welcome to our session, which I just forgot the title of.
Digitizing... What are we?
Collections, or Digitizing Collections and Legacy Data.
It looks like there's some awesome talks in this session, so welcome this afternoon
for the next 90 minutes, and I'm going to introduce our first speaker, Wade
Bishop, and he's going to be talking about why metadata matters.
Okay.
Well, thank you all for coming. It's always a great community
to-
Oh, wait
... get involved with and study. I'm a classically trained social
scientist, and you all are my taxa.
It's been very fascinating to learn more about you and
what you do. But our focus this time, and I have to thank my
colleagues, Emily Breaker, Talia, and Kit Lewers,
for helping
set up the method and analyze the data that we collected
from a survey. And you all probably don't need any of
this background. You know metadata matters.
It's the whole point of things. But the reason we have
metadata is, good reminder, it answers questions.
The who, what, where, when, why.
Good metadata is also machine actionable at this point, so it
definitely can help when users are searching for things, but
for a while needs to be machine actionable as
well.
Yeah.
I think that how users perform data queries is key to the
design for information retrieval systems.
I know in many instances, you all are the users, the power
users, expert users of the things that you manage.
But I also want to keep in mind the
What the user actually searches for to determine fitness for use
of the data of the collections.
There was some recent study
in microfossil research that identified a gap
between the metadata properties that were essential for
users to determine fitness for use and what was actually included in the
metadata. So this misalignment can cause issues,
and I think more studies across other disciplines would be
useful.
And y'all are, a lot of you, living this, the process of aggregating bio
collections from the physical items, describing them,
curating them, moving from data to capta, where you
have data that's captured or digitized.
Been a lot of interesting talks on that today.
And then, yeah, the creation of the metadata to make sure that this data can be
integrated, published,
searched,
all of that sort of with the new emphasis on AI readiness, open science,
public access requirements,
it becomes a more important task.
And then many
folks are dealing with implementation schemas directly
mapped to the Darwin Core terms.
There's varied interpretations of some of the terms, which was an
interesting thing for me to learn and better
understand. It does result in some data that
fall short of interoperability with inaccurate,
insufficient metadata,
and this error propagation happens as you aggregate more and more.
So what we did, had a few past qualitative
studies of this community,
looking at talking to different curators and collection managers,
across different types of data, different collections,
and thought, "Okay, finally, I kind of know what some of the answers are, so I
can do something quantitative and have a survey."
But
here we are. I
built on past questions, past studies,
and asked some of the same things just to get job characteristics,
the data storage management, access practices, and
then we added on any of the challenges with
Darwin Core structural metadata implementation.
We got 57 responses, which is good.
I always have to thank every participant.
There is no human subjects research without humans, so thank you all that do things
without any incentive other than maybe you'll hear about it at a conference
later.
There is a paper under review, so there'll even be better ways of disseminating
this to more people.
But yes, it wasn't something where we could do anything generalizable.
About 98% of our respondents were from the US, actually.
So keep that in mind as we go through the findings.
Interestingly, 71% of participants had the job title of collection manager
or curator. There's a long tail of other job titles, but most of my
studies of emerging data professions, job titles are meaningless.
But in this instance, at least because we have a US population, those are the
most popular job titles. And not surprisingly, we have
vertebrates, botany first for the most respondents, but
then vertebrate collections also
a big chunk of our responses.
The
majority of respondents had been in
their position for 10 or more years, so it's skewed to a more
senior
level in their career as well as time and job.
But then the second most was less than five years.
So it was, again, just context for talking through the
findings. 75%, not surprisingly, worked in an academic setting.
And then about half had a PhD, so there's other
credentials, other degrees. But then I always ask, so
open-ended, "Where did you learn the knowledge, skills, and abilities to do your
job?" And
a lot of the people wrote in, "On the job." So it's interesting to
me. There's this conduit of training for these sorts of jobs
and some of the information science pieces that
I cover in my research data management certificate might not have been something
that you had in your curricular training, but something you had to figure
out when you stepped into these roles.
Also not that surprising, the data storage, it was a check all that apply sort of
situation. So we had
cloud-based storage, most people sharing stuff there,
institutionally supported cloud storage.
Some people still have local servers, desktop, laptop, hard drive.
None of this should surprise you. There's just a lot of different ways
to save things. And we weren't clear on how many different places
the same thing was stored.
Data
deposition, so where it was deposited, GBIF, 82%.
That's not surprising. Then you can see the other familiar
faces, usual suspects showing up there for where data
are deposited. On to the most interesting part, the
elements that people had challenges with, about half
record level metadata. We did have some survey attrition at
that point, so
you can see the counts. There's some in double digits, occurrence,
event. Those were some of the elements that people found challenging.
Location, I've heard those stories even today on
how one person interprets it this way and changing it over time,
those sorts of issues. But why are they a challenge?
We just ask, again, open-ended questions of what were the challenges in the fields
and data types that do not map easily to Darwin Core
fields?
And are there metadata that are important
for reuse that you cannot currently map to To the Darwin Core,
and what challenges do you have with the metadata implementation beyond?
So we got a lot of open-ended responses.
Again, this is qualitative data, so some direct quotes will help
contextualize what people thought, but we did code them into four
groups. Simplification of complex data,
that's a challenge when you're trying to have something that's really complicated
and simplify it into a record.
Lack of community guidelines. So yes, I
don't know if I should even say this here, there must be some guidelines telling
everybody what to do about everything, right?
From library science where there's cataloging rules and a
lot of compliance
required
to make it all work. Limited capacity.
This is something that echoes across pretty much any domain and sector
now, and then some others that didn't fit into those.
So what about simplification of complex data?
Many of our collecting events happened on marine trawls
with a begin time location and an end time location, requiring
that we interpolate a single location and
calculate a bounding error radius for each such event.
So, as someone who's not this kind of scientist, I still
teach geographic information and can understand, okay, this doesn't work.
It was built for this particular response, this sort of parameter.
It might not work for this more complicated datasets.
Representing object relationships, so the host may have been collected by person A,
but the microbe was isolated by person B,
so that creates complications of where does this information
go and what fields?
Then just generalized standards,
that are
designed for one thing, well-intended, but might not fit
for the digital objects people are describing
now. And then the whole idea of flattening of structured data.
So,
the Darwin Core Dynamic Properties provides a place to capture this
information.
Its concatenated display of multiple traits makes it difficult to
search. So I'm looking to all of you, too.
I don't necessarily use this data or describe it, but I'm
studying you all. So does anyone of you have help on explaining what that really
means? Anybody? I'm just thinking today,
this flattening of structured data. Oh, well.
We'll have plenty of time for questions and discourse because I want to learn a lot
more from y'all.
I wish Emily was here.
She would be able to talk through this better, too.
Yes, without the lack of guidelines, without community guidelines,
there's not a consensus on how to use Darwin Core fields in
practice or recommending controlled vocabularies, authorities.
One respondent stated, "Specific locality will always present
challenges in Darwin Core as it's often left to
interpretation." So
limited capacity, again, same thing we face.
We do not yet have an integrated data management system that exports
directly to Darwin Core, so most processes are still manual.
Symbiota has many tools for community-derived data improvement and
generation, but is providing very challenging to migrate
that data back into our database records, so this is sort of like the
one direction issue comes up a lot.
So yeah, a few of these other things are just difficulty mapping some of the
terms to specific things. And they mention
bookkeeping information. I always think a lot of this metadata is
administrative metadata, and not necessarily helping a user at all
find things, but things that are crucial for you to know to be able to manage
collections. So,
I don't know if that conceptual difference would help pull that
out.
And then data use, obviously, most everyone said academic researchers are the
users of this data, students, obviously, users of the data.
And then, again, the long tail of what people usually list
is policymakers, commercial uses, those types of
things.
Licensing. I thought this was really interesting, just to get through really quick,
is that when asked about the licensing use for their data, many
people, we had a question with Creative Commons options.
Most were unsure, so this is interesting to me, just
like,
some kind of by-attribution, non-commercial.
A few people ticked the other ones, but the most popular one was, we weren't
sure how the data are licensed. Which is really key for machine actionable
data, so they know what they can use and how,
as machines. I say the joke is computers compute, humans
assume, and they'll just use things without even reading the metadata.
Surprise, surprise.
Also, I just think for discussion, it'd be good to hear from you all about any
ideas on formal training in biodiversity data management,
hearing more of your own stories on how you learned what it is you're
doing, and any other thoughts you have on Darwin Core
terms
as things emerge. Even today with the package and all these other changes going on,
I'm sure some of the things in our study are already being addressed.
But
yeah. Just a conclusion is that my goal next is to study end users, so
if you have a particular community of practice or need a social scientist for
something, that's my goal is to not only understand what's
happening from the curatorial and the collection manager perspective, but what the
end users are using. What's the metadata that are good for them?
What are the elements that matter most?
But yes, this move towards aggregation through standardization can
therefore mask the nuances and decrease the metadata diversity
needed to accurately describe biocollections.
So I can't lose sight of those smaller
microbiomes of description that are actually very useful for
navigating particular collections when we're looking at
standardization for everything.
Let me see. I had one more, I know.
Yeah. The process will require both technical and human infrastructure, workforce
development, sustained participation, and coordination.
So there's a lot of great work that's already gone on.
I just know that there's quite a bit more to do within the context of today.
And accurate, complete, and machine actual metadata matters
to all kinds of different stakeholders.
It enables evaluation of data quality and fitness for use for your users,
and helps drive all of biodiversity research.
So thank you all for what you do.
Metadata's my favorite topic, so I look forward to just more discussion
on this. And I have to acknowledge
my
own sort of institution, University of Tennessee.
This helped fund part of my research agenda.
But next year, I have faculty development leave and a Fulbright fellow that's under
review to pursue this further and really focus on the user side
of all of this.
But yeah, that was it. Thank you. For anyone who participates in social science
research ever, again, it's important. Is there time for a question?
30 seconds.
30 seconds. The answer is no. All right.
Nice.
Does anybody have a question
for Wade?
I pass this on.
Yeah. I think you can just give it
to the next person. Oh, she'll take it in the back.
All right.
Do, do, do.
Short question. Do you plan on maybe doing it, redo that survey to more
respondents to see how that range all over the country?
So yeah, I did a bunch of interviews in 2016 and then focus groups in
2024, and the survey is down, really.
So
I guess I'm leaning towards returning back to qualitative research
methods, because it's hard to generalize and standardize when everything's so
dynamic and diverse.
There we go.
Yes. That's the goal.
The Fulbright is supposed to do that in other countries, so
hopefully that happens.
All right.
Our next speaker is a virtual talk.
I don't know, it's not showing up there.
I think we might need help getting the virtual presentation going.
The National Museum of Natural History in Washington-
But it's not showing up on the ...
Do I need to move-- Oh, there it goes. There it goes.
Screen mirroring.
Whoa.
Is that on there? Sort of.
Oh.
Okay, bear with me.
Sorry.
How do I get it
centered? Here, I'll let you do it. Okay.
It's gone. Oh, there it is.
Okay. And Jessica is- You pulled it from.
It's not here. Hmm? Where did you pull it from? Here? From here.
Oh, yeah. That's it.
This one.
Oh.
We had it, and now it's gone.
Okay, well, while we're waiting, I'm just going to start talking.
Does anybody have community guidelines for Darwin Core implementation for their
community, like written guidelines? What community do you work in?
The French National Museum of Natural History recommends-
Okay
...
written guidelines for not really Darwin Core, but the
implementation of Darwin Core that we use in our software-
Okay
... for our community, so the French Natural History collections to use to
get real example and definition that are maybe sometimes more
clear and-
Sure
... vocabularies and
explain more what is Darwin Core.
Okay.
So they don't have to dive into it, but they can.
Sure.
Yeah, I think that's a really important piece that Wade and I have discussed, and
our
fossil data working group is working on one for using Darwin Core for
paleo data as well, because it's not-
Hi, my name is Jessica Byrd-
Oh
... collections informatics manager.
Okay. I think what we're going to do is we're going to do this.
No, I think we'll just do this. We can get it ... Right?
It's kind of there.
Can we see this? Can you all see this?
Yeah. It doesn't work if you click there?
Oh, sweet. Okay. Jessica Byrd, she's not here,
but Sylvia Orley is here if you have questions afterwards.
Department of Entomology at Smithsonian's National Museum-
Okay
... of Natural History in Washington, D.C.
This is the pinned insect digitization conveyor, image and data transcription
workflows.
First, I'd like to tell you a little bit about our collection.
The USNM Entomology Collection is the second-largest entomology collection
in the world. We have approximately 35 million specimens.
While our digitization efforts are always ongoing,
digitization typically occurs as a project or
curator-driven
If we used traditional imaging and data transcription methods, it would
take a staff of 20 people 67 years to completely digitize
our entire collection.
There's a lot of challenges when it comes to an entomology collection.
First of all, they are not uniform in storage.
We have dry collections, wet collections, frozen, and slide
mounted.
That means that digitization efforts are not one size fits all.
Also, digitization can cost a lot in both time and funding.
If you're not familiar with entomology collections, insects are typically stored,
dried, and pinned with a label pinned underneath the insect.
Pinned insects make up the majority of our collection.
It's estimated that we have over 21 million pinned specimens.
Typically, when digitizing specimens, labels are removed before the specimen
is imaged. Then the labels themselves are staged and also
imaged. Labels then must be replaced on the pin.
It's imperative to keep the labels in the exact order that they were removed.
Currently, we are using a pinned insect conveyor to digitize our
pollinator collection. The project started in 2025 with
a focus on pinned pollinators. This includes groups of bees,
beetles, butterflies, moths, and flies.
Funding, as of today, is for an estimated
360,000 specimens. This is definitely our largest
digitization project to date.
The pinned insect conveyor requires a multi-step workflow, which includes
pre-curation, imaging, and a virtual data-driven workflow.
Before a specimen sets foot on the conveyor, it goes through pre-curation
process.
We choose a taxonomic group, and then we will image that entire genus.
Taxonomy is vetted and necessary updates are made to our collection management
system called EMu.
Then we run a crystal report to create new header labels for each
individual unit tray.
These header labels serve many purposes.
First, they identify the species that is in the tray.
Second, they assign a unique identifier so that we can trace back
the specimen to the exact unit tray it came from.
Finally,
the taxonomy is embedded in the QR code, which allows it to be stored
in the images metadata. This streamlines the process of catalog
record creation later.
Unique drawer identifiers are also assigned at this point.
Drawer names are used to name the folders so that all specimen images within
a folder stay together. Once specimens have gone through
pre-curation, they are moved to the digitization suite.
I'd like to show you a quick time-lapse video of the conveyor in
action.
As you can see, black boats hold insects and they
move around the conveyor into the photography area.
Photography occurs inside that black box.
Conveyor operators can
image around 500 specimens per day.
As you just saw, specimens are prepared by the object handlers.
The insect labels are removed from the pin, and they're staged on a flat
surface. The specimen is placed also on a vertical stage.
At this time, they assign the specimen a unique identifier.
We typically call those a USNM barcode.
The pinned specimen is placed on the boat, and the boat goes
around the conveyor
until it is photographed.
All unique identifiers, meaning the unit tray, the drawer,
and the specimen ID, are scanned and become a part of the metadata for that
specimen's image.
As the specimen goes on the conveyor, a silhouette of the specimen is
taken to determine the imaging sphere, which determines the
resolution.
Three focus stacked images, about 30 slices each, are taken,
as well as an image of all the labels.
All metadata is stored in a JSON file.
Here's an example of the three diagnostic specimen views.
This example is from sphere one with a resolution of
7,968 PPI.
We have a naming convention for all files that fits into existing
entomology data standards, but are simplified for mass
digitization.
This view is the frontal view.
We also have a lateral view
and the dorsal view.
Finally, here's the composite image of the labels.
Also, individual images of each label
are saved.
After the specimen's imaged, the files are sent to DPO.
This is where we start the virtual data process. Here's a large overview.
To summarize briefly, images are given to
DPO for delivery. They go through a series of quality control measures.
Accepted images enter our digital asset management system called
DAMS. From the DAMS, we automatically create and publish
skeletal records into EMu We also have a simultaneous workflow
going where specimen label data from the label images are
transcribed, so that data can later be appended to the catalog records
in EMu.
A major aspect of this project is quality control.
For this, we use a program called OSPRY.
OSPRY is an open source application that was developed in-house by
DPO. You can find the source code on GitHub.
Also, there is a public side to OSPRY, so you can see images
in real time before they are published to EMu.
Images are assessed to ensure that quality standards are met.
Anywhere from 10% to 40% of the images of a folder are randomly
selected for QC.
We standardize phrasing to document when errors occur.
Errors that can occur on an image can simply be
a skewed specimen
or something larger, like focus stacking issues.
After images are approved and sent to the DAMS, then skeletal
records are automatically created.
Here we have examples of the skeletal records in EMu.
Those are two screenshots from our internal system, which are then
published to our online website in collection search.
Finally, data is sent to the IPT to GBIF.
Due to unexpected challenges with the label images, we had to split the
label image and transcriptions into their own workflow.
During imaging, labels are staged exactly as they are
on the pin, regardless of orientation.
It turned out that post-processing methods were not able to automatically
orient the label images to meet our expected standards.
That's why you'll see in the composite images shared below,
that not all labels are oriented
the same way.
Label image QC typically includes checking for
additional identifiers added, and making
sure that no
labels are cropped off out of the view.
Again, standard phrasing is used when errors occur.
Fortunately, label orientation does not matter for transcription.
We were able to start transcription approximately one year after the
first specimen was imaged. This allowed us to have enough
images of specimen labels for a mass transcription
project.
Transcription will continue until all specimen records have been transcribed.
Currently, we are using a contracted transcription company.
Human transcription is utilized so that all data is fielded
to the correct standard.
Transcription data will be imported into EMu to enrich current
skeletal records, creating fully digitized occurrence records.
Here's a quick overview of our summary statistics.
The conveyor can image up to 1,500 specimens a
day, and that's if all three operators are running.
To date,
191,082 specimens have been imaged and
delivered to the Smithsonian.
That's a total of
584,146 specimen
images and
1,428,078 total
images. That total count includes the individual labels that
we were talking about earlier.
As of today, there are 91,280 specimens
in EMu with their images available.
Transcription is still in the dry run phase, so we do not have
any transcribed data appended into EMu yet.
We hope to very soon.
Obviously, a project this size cannot be done by one person.
We have a huge staff, and we are so thankful to staff at both
NMNH, DPO, and Pictura, but we definitely couldn't do
anything without our NMNH contractors who have
made this project just a joy to work on. Thank you.
All right. Thank you, Jessica.
Jessica is online, so if you go on the Whova app and you have questions,
and Sylvia is also here. Does anybody have a quick question?
Yeah. Oh, Shelly, microphone.
Thank you.
Thank you for the
great presentation.
We just got granted a
big research project with a mass transcription project in
France, and I wanted to know
two quick question. One is
approximate cost of the operation, and the second
question would be
how many of you have experience with transcribing with your own
staff, and how many specimen do you transcribe a day
per
person? Thank you.
So,
the approximate cost, I think of imaging and the transcription
together is about $4 per specimen.
But that's including two different companies.
Secondarily,
of course, this is much faster than doing it by hand.
I can't speak for anthropology. I'm a botanist myself, but
I can say that it's exponential using the conveyor.
Particularly with pin insects, it's a very slow process to take those
labels off the pins delicately and transcribe them.
There was another-
Mass digitization project that was done just by humans,
just people in a row
taking pictures without there. And I think,
trying to remember, it was about a third as slow as
this,
and equally if not more expensive.
So
this is a far better way to do it if you have the funding for it.
Great.
Thank you so much. If you have more questions for these guys, you can find them
online. And our next speaker is Robert Turner.
How are we doing the PDF ones? Are we...
Do you see the page symbol?
I'm Rob Turner. I'm digital operations team lead at Royal Botanic Gardens,
Kew, working within science.
I do actually have a techy background,
but I've been at Kew many years, and I've been acquiring
as much domain knowledge as I can. So I'll be trying
to
explain the seed biology part of these slides to you, as well as the technical
part.
Okay. So,
seed quality. So
why do we want to do seed quality tests?
Because
that determines
whether
the seeds can be stored successfully and germinated successfully.
And the seed quality test is done fairly early in the process.
So we know that those samples are
good enough to store and then
run other tests on, such as viability tests.
So this is what good seeds look like.
These are
images taken of cross-sections of seeds.
So I'll move on to talking about the process
next.
So why do we want to do X-raying rather than just cutting the seeds
to see
whether they're viable or not? So if you do a cut test, it's a destructive
method, so the seeds can't then be stored or used for other
testing such as viability testing.
It's limited to a very small sample size because it's quite labor-intensive
to have to cut the seeds,
and very challenging for small seeds.
So X-raying is non-destructive. The seeds remain intact for
storage. It's rapid and high throughput, and larger
samples can be assessed, and it can be used for small
seeds as well.
So the Millennium Seed Bank Project at Kew is a
long-term ex situ conservation project.
And seeds are conserved through the world's
largest ex situ conservation program, about
105,000 seed collections representing 40,000
species from 191 countries.
And here are some
pictures of the X-ray machines at Kew.
At Wakehurst Place, I should say, which is Kew's other site.
And on the right here is an example of the output
X-ray from that machine.
So
I suppose
simply
the three things that you're looking for in an X-ray are whether the seeds are
healthy, empty, or infested. So on the left here are
some examples of healthy seeds.
In the middle, you can see
some examples of empty seeds with the pointers, and then
on the right-hand side, you can see some examples of infested seeds,
so infested with fungus, for example.
Okay. So Kew's digitization program ran
from 2021 to 2026.
It was predominantly the mass digitization of the herbarium and the
fungarium.
But in parallel, we were working on the Integrated Collections Management System,
or ICMS,
and we were also asked about opportunities for other kinds of
digitization while that project was going on.
So we thought that the X-ray images would be a good candidate for
that,
in that we had
So 21 years worth of images stored on a network
drive, inaccessible to external scientists and
actually most Kew staff as well.
So our goal for
unstructured data like this is to store it in the correct institutional
repository. So for things like documents, they go into SharePoint,
but for images, they go into our digital asset management system,
or DAMS.
And we also identified that the seed X-ray images have the potential for
AI-driven research, so taxonomic identification,
morphological development, germination and viability,
identifying infestations, and mechanical damages.
So
I mentioned the ICMS project. So this was a project to
bring together all of Kew's collections data into a single system,
with a
core entity of occurrence. So all the data's
centered around that core entity.
And then
all occurrences are linked to
the World Checklist of Vascular Plants, or POWO
as most people know it, or Index Fungorum in the case of fungi.
So we have those kind of standards
in terms of our taxonomy,
and also geography standards like the Chadwick geography
and ISO.
So Earthscape facilitates the management of this kind of data by
separating out collection objects from occurrences.
So an occurrence can have many collection objects associated with
it.
So you might, for example,
collect a herbarium specimen and a seed collection and a living collection at the
same time, but it's all the same occurrence.
So
when we promoted the X-ray images opportunity to the senior
stakeholders,
we were asked to look at how we could also add value so it's not just
purely
a legacy data migration task. So
we decided that being able to add a grid and a scale bar would
be a useful addition to those images to make
them more useful.
For that, there's a three-part process, and the first part was to do the actual--
Sorry, I'll go back to the previous slide
if I can. No.
So the first part of the process was to generate the images, the second part
to get them into our digital asset management system, and the third part
to link them up to our actual collections data.
So the first part of the project
was to use a set of Python-based tools
to
read the image resolution in and extract the DPI
from the image metadata or the DICOM file, which is
the raw data file,
and then calculate the pixels per centimeter to create the grid intervals
according to the resolution, and then to generate evenly
spaced coordinated grid sequences
for the particular image dimensions and add the text label as well.
The scale accuracy is then validated
against the physical seed length measurement
from a representative sample.
And so here's an example. So the original one on the left and on the
right we have one with the grid and the scale.
Can you see the grid lines on that from there? Yeah. Okay.
Okay, so Kew's digital asset management system.
So we use something called
Digifolia, which is a third-party product
made by a company called Eutopia.
So the process to get these images into Digifolia was very similar
to the one that we used for the herbarium and fungarium digitization.
Digifolia has an extensive metadata schema,
but in this case, we just need to really be able to link to the object.
So we only stored a catalog number in these cases, and then the
metadata is actually in our integrated collection management system.
So Digifolia is internal to Kew only, but
when we were developing Plants of the World Online a few years ago, we
recognized that we needed to have a way to make images available with fast
access.
So when the workflow is complete in Digifolia,
an external JPEG file is generated on AWS S3
storage
with a CloudFront URL, which we generate using a key.
Okay.
So the next stage then is to make the link within Earthscape using
the asset ID from the digital asset management system and the
externally available URL that I mentioned just now,
and then we can import that into our
Earthscape system, and the curators can then work
with the images alongside the data,
which makes it much quicker for them rather than having to go to files
and find everything.
I should mention one thing. I mentioned we have extensive metadata in the
DAMS that we're not using in this case, but I think
one thing we would like to do is have a periodic refresh of that data for
people who are searching within the DAMS rather than within
Earthscape, so they can find anything for a particular species, for example.
Okay. So how do
we make our data external? So we have the data portal.
So this is a piece of software based on
ALA, the Atlas of Living Australia software.
And we've taken that open source product and
Kew branded it and made a few changes where
necessary.
For the seed bank, we have a fairly limited number of records at the moment
because
there's a lot of material agreements
with
countries about their seeds, and it's not always clear whether the
material agreements align with data agreements.
So we're going back through that process at the moment of just checking to see
whose data can we actually show.
Which leads me onto the next project, which is the Seed Pod.
So Seed Pod will be the portal for the entire
MSB partnerships, and not just the data we hold, but the data that the
partners hold as well.
So getting those data agreements are
going to be really important to be able to show the volume of data
that we'd like to, but the seed x-ray images will go out
via that platform as well. And at the moment, this
is slightly more data rich in that
the data portal is just occurrences, whereas this drills down into the
objects, their processing data, and the viability test
data as well.
And some thank yous. So,
the digitization project was funded by Defra, which
is a department of government in the UK.
I'd like to thank everybody who's worked on the seed bank
projects
over the years, which has made this possible, and the
amazing ICMS team
within Kew,
and our supplier at Earthscape, of course, as well.
Thank you.
We have time for a quick question, 30-second question. Anybody?
Sylvia.
Is this working?
Yeah.
Okay. I was wondering
why you chose not to use a super resolution
microscope for the same work? Is it just quicker and
cheaper to do it with an X-ray, or? I was just curious.
I think so. I think also being able to see the X-ray allows you to see
into the seeds, whereas the microscope, you'd still have to cut them first.
Is that right, Udy? Yeah.
Well, we have a confocal-
Yeah
... microscope that you can see internally, but it's slow.
So I was just wondering if you could try that.
It might just be the equipment we have at the moment, I
think is probably the biggest factor there.
All right. Thank you so much.
Okay. Thank you.
All right. I'm afraid to touch this, but we'll try.
I did hear from other rooms, they're also having technical difficulties, so it's
not just us.
I guess that makes us feel better. Okay. Makes me feel better.
Our next speaker is Matthew Austin from the Missouri Botanical Garden.
Yeah. Thank you.
Take it away.
And I'll pull mine up. I have a PDF too.
Okay.
Well, thank you all for being here.
It's really a pleasure to be here today to talk about some of our work.
And it was also neat to hear about
using X-rays to capture information from plants.
I'll be talking about using another type of data,
spectral reflectance, to add even more information
from plant collections. And in
particular, I'll be talking about how at the Missouri Botanical Garden,
we are integrating the measurement of spectral reflectance from
leaves of herbarium specimens into our herbarium digitization
workflow.
So when we think about herbarium digitization, we often think about it as
having two layers.
One layer is the image of the specimen, and the
second layer is the transcribed label data.
And collectively, these two layers give you information about the
specimen's morphology, taxonomy,
collection, location, date, and so forth.
But there's a whole variety of additional information that can be captured from the
physical specimen, mobilized online, and attached to
this digital record of the specimen.
And at the Missouri Botanical Garden, one of those types of
information that we're particularly interested in is spectral
reflectance.
So what exactly is spectral reflectance, and why do we care
about it?
Well, spectral reflectance, simply put, is light reflectance
data. And
a more technical definition is that spectral reflectance is the
percent of light reflected by a surface across different wavelengths in
the electromagnetic spectrum.
And it's important because it encodes information about
the physical and chemical properties of whatever material is being
measured. So when you're taking a spectral reflectance measurement from a
leaf, you're capturing information about the plant's
chemistry and phenotype that are hard to capture in
other methods.
And you can use spectral reflectance to infer the value of a
variety of functional traits, and this data can be
used to assist with species identification.
So in 2024, we were fortunate to receive
philanthropic support to digitize our entire collection
of around eight million specimens.
And
in addition to digitizing our
collection, taking images and transcriptions of all of the
specimens in our collection, the support also is allowing us to
integrate the capture of spectral reflectance as a
third layer of digitization.
And I'll note that our herbarium, prior to this
project, had around two million specimens already
imaged and around four million transcribed, so this is finishing
out our digitization for the imaging and transcriptions.
And the spectral reflectance isn't being captured for every specimen in
our collection, but only a subset of our collection.
One third component of this project that I won't get into
detail about in this talk,
but I'll give a shout-out to and would be happy to talk about if anyone is
interested, is this also allowed us to launch a curatorial mentorship
program where all of the 18 digitization
staff hired on through this project are paired with a curator at the
Missouri Botanical Garden, and they get to learn taxonomic expertise in
one or more families and can actively help curate our collection.
All right. So the workflow that we follow for this
project begins by taking high-resolution images of
specimens using in-house digitization
photo stations,
where when specimens are imaged, they also receive a
barcode to serve as a unique identifier.
And after imaging, we send our images off to our
external transcription partner, Max Communications,
where they transcribe our specimens, send us our data back,
and we provide in-house quality
assurance on those data before uploading them to our collection management
system, Tropicos.
But in parallel, after specimens are imaged and
barcoded, they're also sent to our spectral measurement team,
where they take spectral reflectance measurements of leaves of
some of our specimens.
And the general workflow that we follow for taking these spectral
reflectance measurements is one where we're taking
three measurements per leaf surface for every
specimen. So something that I'll call out here is that we are
not taking spectral reflectance images of
entire specimens. Rather, we're taking point measurements of
specific areas on the leaves of specimens.
So this is simply spectroscopy for
herbarium specimens.
And
this technique cannot be done for all specimens because
we always have to ensure that we are taking a
measurement of a leaf on top of a non-reflective black
background. So this has to be done
on leaves that can be lifted from the herbarium
paper or that are stored in a fragment packet of an herbarium
specimen. And we take these measurements with the leaf on top of a black
background to ensure that whatever surface the leaf is on
top of is not affecting our spectral measurement.
We also restrict this work to specimens that
don't have contamination, like leaves that are heavily
glued or have pathogens or other types of contamination that might
affect our reflectance values.
So after we take our actual reflectance measurements,
we also capture a whole variety of metadata
associated with each individual scan, which will be
important for downstream analyses to be able to understand
the context in which the scans were taken.
So metadata that we're capturing, there's a whole variety of fields, but
some of them include the surface of the leaf that was measured,
the developmental stage of the leaf, the perceived specimen
preservation, and if there did happen to be
glue, pathogens, or other types of contamination on the area of the
leaf that was measured, we record that so that we can note it for downstream
analysis.
And this spectral
measurement protocol and the associated metadata, we
collaboratively developed with a group of like-minded researchers who are
all interested in taking spectral reflectance measurements from herbarium
specimens, which we call iHerbSpec, or the
International Herbarium Spectral Digitization Working Group.
And we first convened a little more than two years ago
and have developed the first standardized protocol for taking
spectral reflectance measurements from herbarium specimens with
file naming conventions and standardized
metadata fields that all of us in this group are using
for our own collections to ensure that we can
have our data be interoperable across institutions and reusable
into the future.
So today, iHerbSpec consists of more than 30
institutions, and we aim to meet in person
annually at least once per year.
We held our second annual in-person meeting at the Missouri Botanical Garden
this past May, where we discussed a governance structure for our
group and reviewed how the protocol went in its
first year of deployment at our respective institutions.
And we're a very open group, so I'll note that if anyone
listening is interested in being involved, whether you're taking these measurements
now or are just interested in this technique,
please reach out and we'd be happy to have you.
In addition to our annual in-person meeting, we also
aim to meet virtually around once a month.
So there's a lot of opportunity to become involved.
So back at Missouri,
once all of these data are taken, once we have our images, transcriptions,
spectra, and associated metadata, they're all uploaded
to our collection management system, Tropicos, and are
automatically linked with one another using the specimen barcode as a
unique identifier.
Because we take multiple spectral measurements per specimen, there
are additional fields in the file name of
spectral files that allow them to be associated with their unique metadata
on the scan level. And for any files that did
not automatically match, we also have a UI in Tropicos
where our digitization staff can go
and try to identify errors to manually fix to allow any
files that didn't automatically link to then be matched with one another.
So to date, in this project, we have imaged
around 1.55 million specimens, and of
those, around 1.25 have attached label data in
Tropicos.
And we additionally have more than 16,000 specimens with
spectral reflectance data.
So you'll note that taking these spectral reflectance measurements is much
more time intensive than taking a traditional specimen image.
There's specimen selection involved, and you're taking multiple measurements per
specimen.
And in addition to
only being able to do this with specimens that meet our scanning
criteria, we're also, for now, restricting
which specimens we take spectral reflectance data on to
those that are both of woody taxa
that Missouri Botanical Garden curators have taxonomic expertise
in.
So
after we have these data, of course, the interesting question is what can you do
with them?
And one
area that we've been particularly interested in is
training clade-specific species identification models on
spectra to then deploy on specimens
without a species level identification.
And we found that when you restrict to specimens that
are expert identified, so only those ones where you can really trust the
determination,
you typically get accuracies in the
90%.
So here, for example,
this is a confusion matrix for a species identification model
trained on reflectance spectra in the genus Pleurotherium in the
family Lauraceae.
How you can interpret this plot is the true identification of
specimens is on the Y, the predicted identification is on the
X-axis, and then the numbers in each cell are the
percent of times the model predicted specimens
of the true identification as each of these predicted identities.
So if the model is performing correctly, you expect this nice diagonal
running from the bottom left through the upper right.
And you can see that for many of these, we have accuracies in the mid-90s
or up. And over on the right is an example
of one Pleurotherium specimen that is sterile, so it's
lacking reproductive material. We couldn't identify it to species
based on morphology, but the spectra are predicting it
as Pleurotherium insigne 100% of the time.
So this is a method you can potentially use for
specimens only with leaf data to assign a species level identification.
So if you take away anything from this talk, I think there are three main
takeaways.
One is that spectral reflectance adds a new type of data to
digitized herbarium specimens,
and it's possible to integrate these spectral measurements into a
large-scale digitization workflow.
And if you mobilize these data online and attach
them to the
digital representations of specimens, the image, and the transcribed
label data,
they help build out the extended specimen.
And by standardizing this technique across institutions who
are interested in it, we can allow these measurements to
be interoperable and reusable into the future.
So I'd like to give a big thank you to everyone who's been involved in this work,
including a thanks to our funder, and I think we might have a
few minutes for some questions.
We do have a minute for questions if anybody in the room has a question.
Yuri has a question.
Thank you, Matthew, for your wonderful presentation.
My question is how you calibrated your method for
spectral reflecting measurements, because my knowledge as a
botanist, so
live plants and dry plants are completely different, and
you know
them.
But probably, you are measuring only
dry plants. But how are you
dealing with, for example, conditions of
drying cuticle,
measuring young leaves in apical part of
the stem or mature leaves? So cuticle
conditions may be completely different in young leaves and
mature leaves. Then density of hairs.
So young leaves usually have more dense
possess some other things. Then
how are you taking into account different conditions of
preserving or drying plants?
Yeah.
For example, in the tropics,
we use alcohol for preserving.
Some herbaria use freezing,
others use hot treatment of plants.
So
measurements could be different in these conditions.
Yeah.
How you are
actually calibrating your method?
Yeah, those are great questions. I'll take them quickly one at a time.
So first, you're exactly right, spectra will be different between
dry and living plants. In particular, with dried
plants, you're losing information from the bands related to water content.
So that's an active area of research, whether you can
use spectra from herbarium specimens to infer information
from spectra from living plants. There's more work needed to be done
there, but I think it's a promising avenue.
I'm going to
pause us.
Got to cut me off? Okay.
I'm going to cut you off, but you guys can connect afterwards-
Great
... because I think this is actually a longer conversation for you guys to have.
Okay. Thank you.
But that was a great talk. Thank you so much.
And there's a tea break very soon, so you guys can reconnect.
Oh, gosh. Now I have to change this again.
Can I do it?
Maybe.
Okay. Our next speaker is Dmitry Dmitriev,
and
all right. Take it away.
Yeah. Thank you.
Back to insects.
I'll start with a thank you slide. So this is
a species file group at the University of Illinois
I'm working on.
So we have
several members working on the three bigger project,
TaxonWork/TaxonPages,
Catalogue of Life, and
Global Names. We also have some
top collaborators in Argentina.
And I will
speak about TaxonWorks, not actually much about TaxonWorks,
about public interfaces, but TaxonWorks is a
collaborative platform, open access platform for both
developers and researchers,
basically anybody working on the taxonomy, collection
management,
identification tools,
bibliography, et cetera.
This is a great platform to work on.
I'm involved in development, but I'm also involved in the
managing of world Auchenorrhyncha database.
It's a group of hemipteran insects,
leaf hoppers, plant hoppers, cicadas,
et cetera.
So I started working with a personal project, which was
Microsoft Taxes database, and essentially it was a
single-person project, or just few collaborators
joined it.
And with the development of TaxonWorks and the data migration,
the group of collaborators significantly
increased. So I now have
66 registered users in the project.
Many of them edit data, but some of them just joined
the project because they have access to
more advanced tools for filtering data and
viewing data than public interfaces.
So I
won't go to the details of the complicated structure of TaxonWorks
itself. I will focus on the public interfaces, which is a
typical species page. So public interfaces,
all of them around taxon pages.
So you have images, you have synonymy,
nomenclature history,
some additional information about type specimen, gender,
forms for the species name, distribution maps.
In this case, it's distribution based on the
specimen level data. It's another species.
It doesn't have specimens, but it has country, state level
distribution.
For the higher taxa, for the genera and up,
distribution is aggregated basically based on the
distribution, all
included species
in the group.
Distribution records,
again, country and states with all the bibliography, with all the
citation.
Everything is downloadable. There is a button on the top right,
so you can click and get all the information.
Biological associations, mostly host plant data, but there are
some also
parasites and
transmitted diseases.
Again,
table
classification for the plants. So inside of TaxonWorks, I can
filter by plants as well, but
inside of public interfaces, it's just
table of the data.
There is direct link to the iNaturalist, so we can pull the
research grade quality images and show them on
the pages as well.
We have a
number of tools built on the system.
We have interactive keys, where you have a list of characters
or descriptors,
and the list of
taxa which could be identified.
This actually was built by collaborators, not by me.
So some of the character states might have images, so
you can just directly click on the image and get filtering
based on this. You can select more than one if needed, if you're not sure which
one. So this is great collaborator from Saudi Arabia who did a
lot of the matrices and interactive keys inside
of the project.
Dichotomous key,
and actually, it's the key I was building in
terms of revision of one of the genera I was working on.
But the nice thing about this, because we started from the matrices,
from the morphological matrices in the first place, so we built the tools
which helps to
migrate the data from the matrix and build dichotomous key
based on the morphological data.
For many taxa, we don't have identification tools, but we have a lot
of images, so we built this, what we call image
matrix or pictorial key. So we can
have standard views of certain morphological features of the species,
so we can quickly look and compare taxa
from one to another. And again, this is images
made by my collaborator.
And great guy. He is just a student.
He just finished his master PhD and just moved to the
PhD in Arizona
State University. But again, within year and a
half or two years, he uploaded 28,000 images to the
system. So
it's
just get amazing. So we have, besides just the direct
involvement in the project development, we have a lot of
input from different researchers, and we have actually a
direct link to report the data, missing data,
some errors, et cetera, some suggestions.
People can click a button and get to GitHub.
So we have open issues. We have a lot of closed
issues. Some people prefer to still use email.
It's also fine with me.
So we directly involved with Catalogue of Life.
We're sharing data with Catalogue of Life,
and this is a checklist.
And last year, I did a presentation where I did
a comparison because a couple of years ago, Catalogue of Life
introduced extended release of the Catalogue of Life,
where they get data from the existing catalog and
try to enhance it with data from all different other sources.
So this is actually a comparison. I just did it two years ago.
So,
last year I presented that there was some data I was
able to extract from the extended release, some species which was
missing in the database. But I also presented that there is a lot
of
extra unneeded information introduced to
this cluster of the data. And you can see the difference in the number
of species. So last year it was a difference like 500
species. Now it's still like 200 species, and
I'm still positive that most of those are probably misspellings or
historical combination or whatever it is.
I didn't check it on the recent one.
But they also have two validation tools.
In TaxonWorks, we actually have pretty great validation.
So we basically included all the
nomenclatural rules. So everything like priority rules,
homonymy, et cetera. We can get this information inside of
TaxonWorks. But
Catalogue of Life doing their own validation and some of those validation, some
of them just technical. So even if it's marked as red, it's not that bad
as it's look like.
But some of their validation could be useful for validation
of the data in the project.
Distribution record, both specimen level and country state level
distribution shared with GBIF, and you can see a nice
map. Most of the species has at least one point of
distribution. We try to get at least whole type record in the database,
but
still not everything has distribution.
And recently, I started tracking iNaturalist.
So iNaturalist also getting data directly from
TaxonWorks for this particular project.
They started doing it on their own, so basically they was harvesting web
pages, and we pointed them that we have nice API, so you can
get everything directly instead of just trying to grab the data from the
web pages. So they're using our classification, not through the Catalogue of
Life, but directly from TaxonWorks.
But they have their own community, so they have some discussion about nomenclatural
issues. Some people I know, so they may report to me, but
some people still prefer to discuss it in
their own bubble, I would say.
I try to convince people get directly to me, but still
tracking the issues on the system.
I wouldn't go that far with that. I will just finish with
that. If anybody interested and
have any question about TaxonWorks, TaxonPages,
about anything else on the TaxonWorks,
I will be happy to answer.
We do have time for a quick question.
I will also say I have played around in TaxonWorks, and it's very cool.
Thank you.
And I have lots of ideas. Holly and I have been testing it for our fossil
taxonomy project. So
yeah, it's very powerful if you are
A taxonomist
It looks simple on the public pages, but it's much-
But on the back end
... much more complicated on the back end.
Yeah. I was very impressed with what it could do.
Any quick question?
Okay. Well, you guys know where to find Dmitri after this, and we have-
Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you. That was a great talk.
Thank you. We have one more
virtual presentation, which I'm going to see. Oh.
Okay, it says, "Do not use the version that's on here."
So I'm not going to click anything. We have an expert coming to help me.
I'm a paleontologist.
It's this one. Oh, that one. Okay. Got it. Right.
Thank you.
Good day, everyone, and thank you for the opportunity to present our work.
My name is Eunice James-Boyung-
But we can't see it
... from the Medical Entomology Museum at the National Institute
for Communicable Diseases in South Africa.
Today, I'll be speaking about digitizing heritage for science
and how the Medical Entomology Museum can function not
only as a repository of historical specimens, but as a
platform for biodiversity research and vector-borne
diseases surveillance. I will take you through the journey from
a physical specimen to structured digital data,
and ultimately to information that can be useful
for research and public health.
The Medical Entomology Museum has its roots in South Africa's early
response to malaria and other vector-borne diseases.
The Department of Entomology was established in 1925
under the headship of Dr. Alexander Inkela, initially
in response to public health needs. Dr.
Walter Desmier subsequently conducted extensive
surveys of mosquitoes in malaria-affected parts of the country.
These early activities generated specimens that documented
mosquito diversity, distribution, and disease vector
research. So when we look at this collection today, we are looking
at a century of scientific activity.
Digitization gives us an opportunity to take this historical
evidence and make it discoverable and
reusable for modern research.
So what exactly has been preserved over this century?
The museum currently preserves approximately 60,000 medically
important insect specimens, including around 12,000
Anopheles mosquitoes.
The collection includes
pinned
specimens,
specimens mounted on slides,
specimens preserved in different media,
historical collection, type material, and reference
vouchers.
Approximately 80% of our mosquito collection,
including the Anopheles records, have already been
digitized. I describe the physical collection as
scientific infrastructure because these are not simply objects
stored in cabinets. They are vouchers that can be
revisited for taxonomic verification,
morphological examination, imaging, and, where
appropriate, molecular research.
In this photograph here,
we show the pinned specimens of our collection in their original labels,
and this illustrates one of the most important concepts
behind our digitization program.
Every physical specimen in our collection is also
potentially a data point. The label may tell us the
taxon,
where the specimen was collected, when it was
collected, where it was collected, and sometimes the
collection method that was used or other information.
The specimen itself remains the voucher evidence.
When we digitize this information and connect it to the physical
specimen, we transform a museum object into a structured
biodiversity record. So digitization is not
simply about entering information into a spreadsheet.
It is about preserving the relationship between the
specimen and the scientific contents.
So the next question is: how do we make this historical record
usable?
In this slide, we summarize our digitization workflow.
We begin with inventory and accessioning so that the specimen
is properly accounted for.
We then transcribe the information from legacy labels and
records. The taxonomy has to be
standardized because names and classifications can change
over time. Historical locality information
must also be cleaned and, where possible, georeferenced.
The record now goes under quality control before
they are prepared for publication and integration.
The goal is to move from the FAIR principles.
FAIR means findable, accessible,
interoperable, and reusable. And
interoperability is particularly important for us.
We do not want to create a digital database that
simply becomes another isolated cabinet.
We want this data to eventually be able to move across
systems, disciplines, and generations.
Once specimen records are converted into structured data, we can
start asking questions that will be very difficult to answer by
simply looking through museum drawers.
We can analyze records across taxonomic,
geographical, and temporal dimensions.
For example, we can examine where particular mosquito or insect
specimens were historically recorded, how this
known distribution compares through time, or where there are
important sampling gaps. The image here you can see
also demonstrates the link between the collection, temporal research.
Here is the distribution mapping, morphological
identification where we identify the species, and laboratory
investigation. And an important advantage of the natural history
collection is that the physical voucher remains available.
So if an identification needs to be reconsidered, we can then
return to the specimen. That takes us from simple
digitizing records to actually generating
biodiversity intelligence.
Digitization should not be the endpoint.
The real scientific value comes when these records become usable
evidence. Digitized collections can provide a
historical baseline for distribution mapping,
temporal comparison, and trend analysis.
The example here you can see illustrates how entomological
data can contribute to scientific publications and malaria
vector surveillance outputs. Importantly, museum
data do not replace contemporary surveillance.
Instead, they provide historical context that can make
contemporary observation more meaningful.
If we know what was recorded in a locality several decades
ago, we have a stronger basis for interpreting what
we are observing there today.
This is where the work becomes particularly relevant to public health.
We can start with historical vouchers and ask, where was this
vector recorded before? We can use the physical collection for
taxonomy verification and ask, are we actually comparing the
same species? We can then combine that information with current
surveillance to ask, where is the vector occurring now?
And when these different sources of evidence are brought together, we can
begin asking the more important question: what has
changed? And what might that change mean?
So biodiversity informatics and vector surveillance are not
separate activities. Digitized voucher collections
can strengthen surveillance by improving identification,
comparability, and analytical readiness.
This reflects the established role of medical entomology
museums in preserving surveillance specimens and providing
reference material for accurate identification of
field-collected specimens.
Digitization is also particularly important when we look at
orphaned or under-curated collections.
These collections may contain irreplaceable specimens, but they can
be vulnerable because their associated information may be
incomplete or at risk of being lost.
Rescuing such a collection, therefore, involves much more than physically moving
specimens. We need condition assessment,
accessioning, curation, metadata recovery,
and integration into the museum database.
Because a specimen without its associated content
loses much of its scientific value.
Our approach can therefore be summarized in three statements:
preserve the specimen,
preserve the data, preserve the provenance.
A sustainable collection also depends on people.
The museum supports training in taxonomy and species
identification, curation and preservation,
georeferencing, data quality, and biodiversity
informatics.
In these pictures, we show some of our training and engagement activities.
Our collections support postgraduate students,
researchers, surveillance personnel, environmental health
practitioners, and public engagement.
This is important because digitization is not only a
technological process. We need people who understand the
specimens, their taxonomy, their history, and the quality of
their associated data. So sustainable means
preserving expertise as well as specimens.
So where are we going from here? Our priorities are to continue
and complete legacy digitization, strengthen
taxonomic verification, and georeference historical
records. We need to continue integrating
orphaned collections and improve interoperability between
our data and broader biodiversity information systems.
But ultimately, the objective is not simply to
have more records in our database.
The objective is to mobilize these datas for research and
surveillance. So the direction of travel is from
preserved heritage towards accessible,
reusable, and research infrastructure.
I would like to leave you with one central message, that natural history
collections are simply records of the
past. When historical specimens are properly curated
and their associated information is digitized
standardized and made accessible, they become reusable
scientific evidence. They can support taxonomy,
biodiversity research, environmental
interpretation, and vector surveillance.
For the Medical Entomology Museum, digitization does not replace the
physical collection. Instead, it renews the scientific
life of a century-old collection.
So our message is this: preserve the specimen,
mobilize the data, extend science.
I would like to acknowledge the organizations and people who made this work
possible. We gratefully acknowledge the Natural History
Collection, the National Science Collection Facility, and SAMBI
for supporting our collection digitization and orphan collection
activities. I also acknowledge our colleagues, staff,
students,
present and past, within the Vector Control Reference Lab
and Vet Research Institute for Malaria.
We also appreciate our national and provincial Department of Health
collection partners and collaborators who contribute
specimen data, expertise, and support.
And finally, I acknowledge my mentors, Professor Maureen
Gusia, Professor Lisette Kokumo, and Professor Basil
Broo for their contribution and support.
Thank you.
That was a great talk. The collection manager in me is very happy.
Okay, is that stopped? Eunice is online if anybody has any
questions for her.
Anybody?
You can also message her in the Whova app.
She's in the chat right now
if you have any questions.
This was a really great session, and I'd like to thank all of our speakers, and
my co-moderator, Shelley.
Thanks for helping. And yeah, I think there's a tea break.
But let's leave with Eunice's message of, what was it?
Curate the specimens, mobilize the data, extend the science.
I love that. That's a great message to have tea on.
All right. Thanks, everyone.
And
then
we'll switch.
Yeah, we'll
do it.
All right. Can everybody hear me? Is that mic?
There you go.
Is there a microphone? Oh, there we are. Yeah. It's just so weird. All right.
Let's see.
Let me just... Yeah, I'm going to take these out of my ear. All right.
I'm half deaf and just sometimes these things are more annoying than they're worth.
All right.
Thanks for coming today. This is the standards. Actually, let's get to the slide.
This is the State of the Collection Description Interest Group, what's happening
and what's not.
I'm your moderator, Ben Norton from Yale University, and this is Sharon Grant at
the Field Museum. We'll be your moderators.
I think you've all gone to sessions all day, so you know how this works.
We have a microphone we pass around.
We have the timing note cards, and it'll be fine. All right.
So why repeat it? All right. So our sponsors, these guys are important.
Thank you, GBIF, PictureAIM, Atlas of Living Australia, Pensoft, BioShare,
EarthKate. Did I get that right? Picture... Okay, good. Cool.
Code of conduct, obviously be nice to people.
And then recording will be on-demand links will be shared afterwards.
Timing, we
will be monitoring the chat, there will be Q&A, so if you do correspond through
that, that's totally fine. We'll answer your question and make sure the speaker
gets the question, and I think we will try to do questions after
talk and not wait till all of them at the end. We'll see how the time goes.
And then, yeah, we'll pass around the microphone.
So let's, Sharon, you're up first.
Let's get started,
and I'm going to start your slide.
No, I'm not first. We've got-
This one, right?
We've got four talks for you today.
Our first one is going to be from Elspeth Haston.
She's at RBGQ, and
she's the Deputy
Herbarium Curator there, and she's one of the
co-conveners for the
MIDS group. So she
unfortunately can't make it, so we have her recording.
So we are going to play that one through first, and we then, unfortunately, we do
have a second recording, so just stay with us.
And then we have a couple of talks. Adam is in the back, and then I'll talk about
LATIM, of course. So just to give you a lay of the land as to where we're going.
So
take it away.
Awesome. Let's get started.
Enjoy the conversation.
Yeah. I'm not going to start in the middle of a sentence.
Back her up a little bit.
Yeah.
We good?
Okay.
Let's do it.
Good morning. I'm so sorry not to be with you in person this year
to enjoy the conversations and ideas that I know
you'll all share. Happily, some of the co-authors will be present to
help answer any questions at the end.
So all over the world, we've been doing an amazing job to
digitize natural history collections.
There's been a growing number of national and institutional programs of
mass digitization.
We've seen an increase in the amount of already electronic data
arriving with the specimens.
The use of community portals, machine learning, and AI are
being used more widely for label transcription.
There are also more and better tools for geo-referencing specimens.
So given all of this, how are we doing?
So we focused on these questions to understand
digitization progress over the years, and we'll go through these during
the talk.
For the study, we explored the data in GBIF.
We limited ourselves to
preserved specimen records
and to biological taxa. Finally, we explored
data that were available during the last 10 years, since
2016.
And in the next few slides, I'll run through the methodology that we
followed.
So we learned a lot about the data in GBIF as we went.
We had originally planned to use the GBIF snapshots, but these have not
historically included all the specimen metadata, so we had to find
alternative data files.
Interestingly, there are users out there who like to request and cite all of
GBIF.
This provided us with access to Darwin Core archives with all the
records and more that we were interested in.
So we had to filter out the massive number of observation records, but we
then had the data that we wanted.
So we used DuckDB
to partition the data and generate Parquet files, and we
ran these through a version of the MIDS calculator
to calculate the MIDS level reached for each record.
And we also included some additional record values for analyzing the results.
So as I mentioned, we learned a lot about the data in GBIF and some of the
challenges in analyzing them. Working with big files needs
big computing resources.
Data formats can always cause problems, and there are some
very surprisingly large values in some GBIF records, including
this one with over 60,000 coordinates.
During the data preparation, we were unable to confidently
use any files for 2017, so we excluded
this year from the analysis.
So going through the questions we wanted to ask.
So first of these was really, in our minds, to confirm our
expectation that we would see a steady progress in digitization over the
last 10 years.
Well, we didn't get the straightforward confirmation.
It was a bit more complicated.
So first of all, a quick review of the MIDS levels.
So there are four recognized levels, bare, basic,
intermediate, and extended.
In the talk, you'll also
hear mention of MIDS level minus one,
just to show that
it's possible not to reach MIDS level zero.
So
overall, the before and after for this 10-year period showed clear
progress with a much higher number of records reaching MIDS level one
as well as passing through to reach MIDS level two.
So there's been progress. It's just maybe not so steady.
While we saw a gradual increase in the MIDS levels over time for numbers of
records, this was matched by the increase in the total number of
records, meaning that the percentage of digitized records remained
fairly steady over the years.
The one year we saw a major change was after 2016
when there was a huge increase in the number of specimen records reaching
MIDS level one.
And we can dig into all of these results a little bit more.
So we can see the impact of enforcing the
license information in GBIF.
We can see an increase in the number of datasets that included the modified
date
for the records, and these are the
pieces that really made the difference to reaching MIDS level one that
we saw earlier.
We can see that the name and identified as are both very
high, and this is mainly due to the use of the GBIF taxonomic
backbone for the data.
So we can also see the start of recording and
submitting people identifiers to GBIF.
These didn't impact the overall MIDS levels of these records because there was
other data missing, but it shows what happens when work by a team of people
make it possible to capture and share data.
So has the increase of electronic records during accessioning
resulted in more complete records being submitted more recently?
A bit.
What's surprising is the variability of new specimen
records coming into GBIF. So instead of seeing nice steady improvements,
we're seeing more variation than we expected.
However, in the last few years, we are starting to see some fewer records
coming in below MIDS zero and the percentage
coming in at MIDS one is rising.
And
this was driven mainly by the more consistent inclusion
of the organization and modified in the specimen record.
So are tools
such as these resulting in the enhancement of more existing
records?
Yes and no.
We're not seeing a lot,
but there is a larger impact in some years than in others.
So 2020, 2021, 2023 in
particular showed some more clearer trend to
increasing the completeness of the records.
Interestingly, the records submitted in 2016
fell from MIDS zero to MIDS minus one by 2018.
So when we looked into this to see what was happening, we found that five
datasets from a single institution accounted for a large
majority of these records. So for two years, these records
dropped the organization data in their submission to GBIF,
and then this seems to have been corrected by 2019.
So which data are proving to be most challenging to capture and share on GBIF?
And it depends on the taxonomic group, but in general,
the kind of preserved specimen,
some of the collecting event information,
media, geographic coordinates, and identifiers.
But if we look at the
three of the kingdoms in the
biological records
to highlight some of the elements.
If we look at
the object type, we can see that Animalia more often
have this recorded,
and this is probably caused by the higher variation in object
type in zoological specimens compared to herbaria.
Media is highest in Plantae, which is not surprising since these tend to be
simpler to image.
Collecting number is more likely to be present in Plantae and Fungi
than Animalia.
And finally, media ID
is higher in Plantae, and it's
possible that the implementation of the International
Image Interoperability Framework, IIIF,
is more common in herbaria.
So finally, some conclusions.
It's not straightforward.
It's
interesting that records in GBIF are not just becoming more complete, some are
decreasing too.
The impact of projects to enhance data can be seen, as we saw
with people identifiers.
The impact of GBIF making some data compulsory can be seen,
as we saw with license.
There are differences between kingdoms in terms of data completeness,
and these show different priorities and challenges.
And specimens are being enhanced over time,
with some cohorts of records in some years improving
faster than others.
And finally, big datasets make a big impact.
So the development of the MIDS standard is giving us a way now
to measure and monitor global digitization effort to see the
impact of all the work being done, and to help us check that the data
that we capture are being made available on platforms such
as GBIF.
And with that, I'd like to say thank you,
particularly to all the members of the TWIG MIDS task group
for all their work over the years.
Sorry not to be with you in person this year to enjoy the-
So Elspeth is online. Anybody have any questions?
No. You can also chat online.
We good?
Do you... Where's your mic?
Yes.
Were you able to evaluate whether mass digitization projects, which might produce a
high volume of records, but potentially at a lower quality, had an
effect or contributed to these numbers?
Elspeth, can you hear that?
Hi. Can you hear me?
Yeah.
Okay.
Yes, it was one thing we started exploring was
categorizing the
datasets by dataset size.
And
because that's something we thought are just some large datasets that are
having a bigger impact.
I think it is an interesting bit to explore.
I think we need to do some more
analyses on that, but I think also we need some additional
data
in our Parquet files to really dig
into it a bit more. But certainly, we're seeing some
really big
datasets with
smaller,
with less data, essentially, lower MIDS levels.
I
thought we would see those increasing over time more.
So I think
I'm still interested in doing a bit more digging to see exactly how these
datasets are improving over time, to see what enhancement is
happening.
Sorry, does that really answer your question? I'm not sure.
Adam's nodding and he has a thumbs up in case you can't see him.
Okay.
Cool.
Thanks, Elspeth. Really appreciate it. Hope everything's going okay over there.
Thank you.
Okay. So-
All right.
How are we doing for time?
I forgot I'm mic'd up.
I like having my inner dialogue broadcasted over room. It's wonderful.
So-
Are there any questions in the chat?
There are not.
Okay.
We need to next one.
Next one? Okay. So next up, while you tee that up at the back, we
have a second presentation that's online from Marie Grosjean.
She's the data administrator over at GBIF Secretariat, if
I can find her thing. Let's get rid of this,
and somewhere here.
This one with over 60,000 coordinates.
I was going
to watch you struggle up here for a few.
You could just watch me struggle.
Confidently.
I can use a computer. I'm in IT.
It's behind us.
They extended the screen.
It's behind me? No.
Yeah.
That's a whole pantomime skit.
It was. All right.
You're American, you don't get the reference.
All right.
There we go.
My name is Marie Grosjean. I'm a data administrator of the GBIF Secretariat.
Oh.
And I take care of GeoRecollect-
It's not working
... the Global Registry of Scientific Collections.
We're going to make Marie stop and start.
Thank you for having me today. I'm sorry I'm not in Oslo
Everyone, my name is Marie Grosjean.
I'm a data administrator of the GBIF Secretariat, and I take care of
GRcycle, the Global Registry of Scientific Collections.
Thank you for having me today. I'm sorry I'm not in Oslo, and I'm sorry if my voice
sounds sick because I'm sick a bit at the time of the recording.
I hope you're enjoying the conference.
Today, I'm going to talk about the Latimer Core standard and the Global Registry of
Scientific Collections.
So first, for those who might not be familiar with GRcycle, I'm going to
explain a little bit what it is. It's a registry of physical scientific
collections and their associated institutions.
So it's really about the content of the collections, the specimens the collection
may hold, where the collection is located, who works there.
But it's also a repository for codes and identifiers.
It is curated by the community. So we have
more than 70, I think, editors who are currently
curating the information, but you can also make update suggestions if you
need. We also have and use external sources.
Index Perorum is actually the main source of data for
GRcycle. You can also link occurrences that are published on
GBIF to GRcycle entries, which allows us to make and
create dashboards. And in addition to that, GRcycle also
has an API, which allows programmatic access, but
also updates to the data.
And GRcycle can be embedded in the GBIF-hosted portals.
I won't go into details, but essentially, the current GRcycle website
is actually a hosted portal.
So on GRcycle, we have all kinds of data, and on one side you
have the collection textual information.
So it's really things like my collection contains
birds of North America or birds of a specific area, for example.
But on the other hand, you may have occurrences that are published on GBIF, and
occurrences are really at the specimen level.
It's the collection of a given organism at a given time and place.
The data in occurrences is highly structured, and
we'll be able to index it in GBIF and make it searchable.
You can search occurrences by country, dates, coordinates, and
so on. So
this is really great for indexing.
But sometimes you have something in between.
You have data about your collection.
It may be more than just a textual description, but you're not
yet fully at the digitized specimen level.
You're not yet at the occurrence level.
Or maybe you have a geological collection which cannot have occurrences on GBIF.
So for capturing the information in between, we created this data exchange
format,
that we named in the context of GRcycle collection descriptors.
So it's for things like, for example, list of collectors
or a list of taxa that you may have in your collection, or things that are
more than just the text, but not quite occurrences.
Collection descriptors are formatted like this.
You have tables, so it's flat tables, and the headers will tell
us what you put in the table. So you can choose to use Darwin
Core terms with the prefix WDC or Latimer
Core terms with the prefix LTC. You can also
choose to share unmapped columns, meaning you can put whatever you
want there and we'll be able to display it, but we might
not be able to recognize the content and index it.
So, for example, typically you will have things like custom statistics, like
the number of image specimen for a given taxon, for example.
So this we can display. It might be of interest for the users, but
it's not something that we can actually index and make searchable.
The Darwin Core terms and the Latimer Core terms, yes.
So a typical Darwin Core term that you could be using in your collection descriptor
is the scientific name. You can upload a list of scientific names for your
collection. Even if you don't have a fine resolution
identification for your specimens, you can still upload a list of taxa,
and then people who are looking for collections that may contain this taxa will be
able to find your collection. So I mentioned that Latimer Core terms can
be used in collection descriptors.
The two main ones that we're indexing currently are biome
type and object classification name.
And this is very helpful because it allows us to be able to index collections
based on things like whether they're an algae collection.
It's not a monophyletic group, algae.
So it's difficult to identify based on the scientific name, what
constitutes an algae collection.
But everyone knows whether they have algae in their collection, or at least should
know.
So now on GRcycle, we're able to search things like marine algae
collections for a given
country, for example. We use vocabulary when possible, and
Latimer Core helps align the vocabularies with what we use.
All the Latimer Core terms can be used to model descriptors.
However, we may not index everything.
The reason for that is that otherwise we'll have a lot of fields that
don't give any data. We need people to upload data to GRcycle first.
Otherwise,
it's a bit disappointing for users.
If you want a good example of a complete collection descriptor, you
can go to the Mace Botanical Garden page, and
these cofounders have uploaded data about the collection there
based on a survey that they ran a few years ago, I believe.
And they have modeled the data as collection descriptors and used
Latimer Core terms. So it's quite interesting to see.
Latimer Core is also used for a data exchange format
of GRcycle data. So basically, you can choose to
export collection or institution data.
You can also update GRcycle
with an import formatted as Latimer Core.
So it's quite helpful, but I'll talk about the limitations now.
So one limitation of our current implementation is that
there are lots of GRcycle terms, fields, that exist in our
database that don't really have an equivalent in Latimer Core, so we have to
model it as measurement of facts.
Which means that unless our end user
knows the measurement types we use, then they won't really be able
to format the data the same way we do.
So it's a bit of a limitation here. We're missing a bit the
terms there. Measurement effects can be a bit catchall.
Another thing that's limited in our current implementation is that
we're missing the collection descriptor part of the
institutions and collections in GR Cycle.
Well, institutions don't have collection descriptors, but the collections do.
And so it's a little bit too bad because it's missing from the export, meaning that
you don't get the full information when you're using the export format as Latimer
Core.
In addition to that, Latimer Core is changing.
The structure is going to be more formalized, so what we're planning for the
upcoming year is to revisit our implementation of
the Latimer Core export so that it includes collection descriptors and it is
compliant with the latest Latimer Core format
recommendations.
We also use Latimer Core in our teaching material.
So GR Cycle has a curriculum for editors, for those who want to be
national editors. And in that curriculum, we
have a collection modeling exercise.
It's a little silly fictional story of a university that
has a museum and also a teaching collection, and the
museum has several sub-collections.
And so we tell the story, and then we want people to think
about how they would model it in GR Cycle, but also in
Latimer Core. And so often the results are quite funny because
everyone has their own idea,
so it's a bit heterogeneous, and it shows also the flexibility of Latimer Core.
But it gives us a common language for modeling collection information, which is
quite nice.
And you can look at it here, the exercise, and also
the version generated by the Latimer Core maintenance group as
correction. And we tested this modeling exercise in a
DISCO-Flanders workshop earlier in May, and this was quite interesting
to see what everyone came up with. Thank you very much.
Thank you for the Latimer Core maintenance group and to people who work in GR
Cycle, on GR Cycle at GBIF, and all the GR
Cycle editors, and also the sources of information for
GR Cycle, including Index Herbarium.
I hope you enjoy the rest of your conference. Thank you for listening.
I should be online to answer all your questions if you have any.
And have a good day. Bye.
Marie is online right now, so.
Hey, chair.
What do you want me to-- Oh, where's the--
Ellie ran away. Hi.
Hi. My question is about the nesting of the
collection,
structuring collection structure.
The main
collection can contain sub-collections, and this structure is modeled by
Latimer Core. My question is whether it is also
reflected in the GR Cycle,
and how it be tackled by GBIF in the future.
Marie, are you there?
I can answer because I was just asking.
I am.
Yeah, go for it.
Yeah, I can.
Can you hear me?
We can.
Okay.
But you can answer otherwise. But otherwise, I can try to answer.
So,
yes, the Latimer Core standard
allows for much more flexibility than
what the current GR Cycle model allows.
We have several possible
workarounds for modeling some
hierarchy, but it's not meant for that at all.
So,
one possible solution, if you want, is there's the
field called the incorporated collections.
So you can
decide to create entries
for each of your collection,
and at each collection levels, and then reference the other collections in it.
It isn't ideal, and it poses
some other challenges, but that's what we have at the moment.
We have, I believe, in the GBIF work program, added a
little bit about exploring how to
formalize relationship between institution entities in GR Cycle,
but I don't have a solution at the moment.
So,
with the current model, the
most you can do is really make a decision
on
the level of representation of your collections.
And then if you do want it to show the relationship between
the different collection levels, then to use the
available fields to mention it, but it won't infer
anything. It will just be information for users who find the collection entry
saying, "Okay, those other collections are there as well." So, does it
answer your question?
Yes. He nodded his head.
More or less.
Yeah. And you also can probably add an issue on GitHub if you
have this issue. I have this issue, too.
And so, they do recognize creating a GitHub issue, and they'll track it, and then
it's a good place to offer suggestions and feedback to them on GR Cycle, so that's
good.
Yeah, but also on the Latimer Core side, that's one of the things.
That's how we end up talking through this with Marie, is she threw a thing
into the GitHub repo, and we saw it, and she came along, and we're
happy to talk through all of the examples to see if we can solve it with you.
Yeah.
Thanks, Marie.
Yeah, thank you, Marie.
Sharing red.
Thank you.
Me next. Yep. So,
hi. Ooh. Talking too loud, apparently.
So I'm Sharon Grant. I'm at the Field Museum in Chicago.
And so
Marie teed this up really nicely for us.
So I'm here to talk you through where Latimer Core is right now,
and what's coming up in the next year with us as
a maintenance group.
So hopefully we'll get through some of these questions with you.
So first up, for those in the room who haven't-- Actually, show of hands, has
anyone not heard of Latimer Core before?
I'm impressed you all heard of it. But I'll tell you who we are.
So we are a maintenance group. We finally got ourselves out from under the
task group label. We meet every month.
We have a GitHub repo, and we have a really long agenda.
There is a QR code there that takes you to our emails.
We would love as many new faces, people with use cases where you
need help with us talking it through.
So please
get in touch, and we will add you. We meet once a month.
You don't have to come every month, but it'd be great to see you.
So Jutta,
Marie, Janine Jones, Ben, Ellie, Martin, and Kate, we are
the people trying to hold onto this.
So at its core, as Marie said, it's a standard that--
Oh, hello. It basically describes intentionally grouped
things.
I think you've heard it a number of times today.
Sometimes you don't have time to do individuated things.
So it's two--
You have the wrong remote. Which one are we doing? Let's see.
No, you're doing right. That one.
There we go. All right. I'm just going to stand here like this. I can do this.
Nope.
What's happening is you're standing with the wrong remote. There we-- Yeah. Okay.
That one. I can see the remote. Here we go. Anyway. Come on. You can do it.
There we go. So Latimer Core is to groups as Darwin Core is to
individual occurrences, at its essence.
So that's what it is.
And we did a bunch of things through 2025.
As it stands right now, we have 15 open issues.
Some of them are bigger than others.
But the main thing that happened was that we had
a bunch of users and people in the community who said,
"This is a great thing, but we
need structure. We need you to tell us how to structure it so that we can implement
it." That was the big message that came through.
So we spent a lot of time this year trying to work out how to do that.
Part of it landed with we needed identifiers for things,
and we couldn't make it machine implementable without them.
So we spent a lot of time talking about that.
We do have two other places that are working with Latimer Core right now.
They haven't done anything public yet, but MCZ Base
and Elvis, we're talking with them about how to implement
Latimer Core. So it's happening.
And then we
did some disambiguation with the tag and with the
TDWG exec about what was the difference between an interest group, a task
group, a maintenance group, a working group, there's all this stuff.
And so
we figured that out. And then we started to really dig in
to the difference between structures and descriptions, and I'm going to
talk you through that and where TDWG has now landed in
terms of standards and defining them and what we have to do
in 2026. So this is a slicey bit in the middle.
Hopefully, I'm not teaching anyone things they don't know.
But I didn't know these things. So
we talk about URIs, we talk about IRIs, we talk about URLs.
There are all these weird acronyms with R in the middle.
And what I had to learn, what we had to learn was what the differences were.
So URIs, uniform resource identifiers, they kind of came
first.
They are a string of ASCII characters that allow you to identify something.
That's basically what that is. So when they talk about URIs, it's that.
So GUIDs are URIs,
UUIDs, DOIs, ArchiDs. If you look at them, you can often read
them. They're in ASCII. But then there's this IRI,
which is an internationalized resource identifier,
and that's got even more terms in it.
So you've now got a bigger pool of characters you can put together to uniquely
identify something. And this gets important down the line.
But I wanted you to know that they're not scary or weird.
They're just
strings of characters that are used to identify something.
Where they get interesting is persistence, right?
We talk about persistent URIs or persistent URLs or persistent
IRIs. A thing is only persistent if somebody keeps
it
in perpetuity and looks after it, and you can access it forever.
That's all that means.
And so the
issue with those is that someone has to take ownership for this string
so that it always exists, and it always means the same thing.
And then to make it really useful, there has to be a service, so that if you use
that string, it takes you somewhere.
And most of that costs money. Not all of it.
And there are increasingly things that don't cost money.
So this is often a big problem for an institution that can't-- Like,
we have 40 million things, and we still can't afford a persistent
URI, IRI, URL thing, string,
because we can't afford it, right?
But we had to work all of this out ourselves,
and once we figured this out, we're like, "Oh,
TDWG uses IRIs."
And when you become a standard,
you can have an IRI for all sorts of things,
and you can get them for what they call vocabularies.
So there's
a thing that looks like a URL,
http://rs.tdwg.org/ltc,
string of characters.
And it's an IRI. We put it in the IRI bucket, and
when you become ratified, you get one of those.
And so we ratified in Okinawa and we got one.
We were like, "Yes, we have this thing.
It's going to last forever."
The documents that TADWIG have also have IRIs,
and they have a slightly different format. So they're the rs.tadwig.org/.
Then there's the thing that goes with the standard, so ours would be LTC, and then
there's a document name, another string
that TADWIG looks after and makes persistent.
That's all good.
And then there's a third set of these IRIs, which are the terms.
And so a lot of you will have seen these with Darwin Core.
There's a URL that goes with every term.
This is where it got really complicated because they don't all mean the same thing.
So
you'll find things that say Darwin Core /IRI, and then
/LTC/ and then a term, and then a thing
that is just some string of characters, but it means a class, and we got really
confused.
Because when you ratify, you're supposed to get all of these things,
and we thought we had them,
but apparently we didn't. We didn't have them for reals.
And when poor old Ben was trying to build automated systems, it
was looking for these IRIs.
And remember I said an IRI is unique and it's persistent?
Well, because of the way we had defined Latimer Core, they were
duplicates, and they didn't mean the same thing.
So now we're in the position where we have to disambiguate all of this.
And part of that came because back when the world was simpler,
TADWIG made a decision to have globally scoped
IRIs, right? Which is good. You only want one string to
identify one thing.
But we came along and went, "Well, we want to use structure.
We don't want to have to do..." I don't know if you were in the talk with the
recorded by and the identified by, and we're like, "We don't want to do that.
We're going to be more generic. We're going to follow a standard." And so we have
identifier, has identifier, which has more than
one of these things in it,
but this might be the collector, and this might be the identifier,
but they still have the same thing in them. So that's a problem.
So we got hold of TADWIG,
and we said, "We need you to help us,"
right? "Because we are so confused right now.
We don't know where we're going, what we're doing."
And Yuta put it really well. She said, "We need to ask TADWIG if they would take
the step from just being a place that holds onto
IRIs for bags of terms."
You've probably heard the bag of term
phrase. "Or are they going to
allow standards with structure and have
structure be part of the formal
standard definition?" And we're like, "You choose.
It's up to you,
but the world needs structure."
And in fact,
they said yes, because
Darwin Core DP was already doing it,
and so was Camtrap DP. And if you notice, those have
either been ratified or are about to be ratified.
So they were doing the thing that we needed, but because the way they were doing it
wasn't documented and ratified yet, we couldn't benefit from
it.
So
what you will now find coming out from TADWIG is a way for a
group to define a standard that's not just
terms.
It's going to be a formal way to say, "This is how you document structure in a
standard. It should look like this." So there will be a way to
group terms,
repeat them,
and as for MIDS, this is another example of there are
terms that MIDS uses that are from elsewhere, and
it's defining a statistic, not a term.
So that needs an IRI. So these are three things that are going to be coming along
the line
out of Darwin Core DP. So Latimer Core
is in the process. We have our terms layer.
We actually ratified with this more or less. I think we have three.
Was it three that were repeated? Something like that.
And we've worked that out. So our terms layer
with the IRIs, one for each term, yay, tick.
We are in the process of doing the DP bit, and the DP bit
is just the structure. How do the terms hang together to let
Marie
group collections and do the kind of thing that you were asking?
So we're in the process of working this out.
We are going to have to go back through a round of ratification.
So this is going to go to public review
sometime this year before Christmas. We're going to not get in the way of MIDS.
We're going to let them go first.
And then the last thing we have to do, this is a bigger thing, and I'm not going to
go into too much depth, but we have to then think about
this conceptual layer, and there are lots of things right now out in the world and
ways to do that, but I won't
take us down that rabbit hole. But there is one more thing, this piece, the
relationships amongst the terms and how we define that.
So that's where Latimer Core is right now.
We're building LTC DP.
I think it's what that turns out to be, and it will go in the bucket with
Darwin Core DP and Camtrap DP. So anyone else out there who wants to
create a standard now, thank you, Camtrap DP, for breaking the ground
and doing it.
Darwin Core, John, thank you for teaching us how
normal people do it, because it was all in the heads of brainy people.
So
Latimer Core is now in the process of doing that, so
look out for that coming along.
And this is courtesy of Ben, just so that you know that we are actually working on
it, and we have actually done something.
This is us-
Stepping back, we actually had a lot of this work done,
but this is our start. We have some work as a
maintenance group to review this and talk it through, and this diagram is
the extension. This is what's going to come up for ratification.
So we're going to need you guys to help us to look at it and tell us if it
works.
But
we did some conceptual things, and then Ben did an amazing job putting it into a
diagram.
We'll get there. So that's where Latimer Core is right now.
Again, thanks to everyone who sits on those calls with us every month and
helps make this happen, because it's fun,
more or less.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Oh.
I have a really, really brief one.
Wait, please wait for the people online.
Okay.
Why is it called Latimer?
It's named after the Latimeria, the coelacanth.
So
it was obviously a taxon that everybody thought was extinct, but the
people who actually were fishing off the coast of Africa knew it wasn't.
But then Marjorie
Latimer
got hold of it, described it, and now we have it back in the world. Go ahead.
Do you want to say something?
Yeah, I just
want to add that
we should do this really
quickly, too, that
all the other standards were named after men, so we wanted to have a woman
as naming a standard, and she was managing a
collection-
In South Africa, yeah
Okay.
I like that question. I can answer that one.
All right, so
Adam, definitely not last, but
definitely the mostest.
Dude, final one of the day. This is good.
Final talk of the day. You made it.
Oh, do you want to-
I got you. There you go.
Just going to bring one up.
Apparently, there are three.
Which one?
Hmm?
There we go.
Got it. Cool.
I'll finish up the voice line.
Cool.
Mic's on. Oh, you got a mic.
Look at this.
Yes, I have one. That's mic right?
Okay. Hi, everybody. My name is Adam Manser.
I am the data manager for the Department of Mineral Sciences at the Smithsonian
Institution.
I'm going to be talking today about using
record quality scores like MIDS to assess the quality of geoscience
collections.
So this is the outline of the talk. I'm going to do a brief intro to the
geology collections at the Smithsonian.
I'm going to talk about our existing record quality metric, which is the Collection
Digitization Reporting System, or CDRS.
I'm going to spend a little time comparing CDRS to MIDS, and
finally, at the end, talk about how we can use these metrics to approach
work in a large collection.
Okay, so this is a photo of the National Museum of Natural History in
Washington, DC.
The museum itself is estimated to include 140 million
objects in its collections, split across seven science departments,
two of which are focused on geology,
which means they contain things like rocks, minerals, ores,
meteorites, and fossils.
Of the two collections, mineral sciences is much, much smaller.
We currently have about 500,000 records.
We estimate that we can represent our entire collection of about one
million objects
with 600,000 records. We're mostly digitized in that
most of our specimens have a digital catalog record.
Paleobiology is a much, much bigger collection.
They currently have about 800,000 records, a little bit more than that,
but they estimate that they would need somewhere between 10 and 13 million
records to represent the 42 million objects in their
collection.
So two collections, two very different scales, very different places
in the digitization pathway.
For people who are not familiar with geology,
the metadata required when you're collecting specimens is actually
pretty similar to what you might expect to see in
digitization, or excuse me, for biodiversity and
biological samples. So you take a specimen, you assign it a
name, a rock or mineral name, or a taxon for
paleobiology. You'd have an object type like a rock or a mineral.
You'd also have the location expressed either as a place name
or through coordinates.
But there's also the additional geologic context, and so
that gives you information about the unit or the age of the
material that you've sampled.
So at the Smithsonian, we use this system called CDRS
to track the quality of our collections.
This is intended as a digitization progress
standard.
So it tracks the completeness of our records relative to
a standard record that consists of the core metadata
that you would expect to find in a complete record.
We track these via primary collections, which are subsets of the
collections defined by the individual collecting units
to organize work in their collections.
The scores are calculated automatically in our
database
via a back-end process, and they're mostly based on a series of
presence and absence checks in the records themselves.
Some of the challenges that we've run into with CEDARS,
rules are inconsistent.
Each of those seven scientific departments
was given latitude to define their own rules, and as a result,
the values produced by the system are not necessarily comparable.
Some rules are conditional. There might be multiple ways that you can pass a given
check, which means that records can have the same score but have different
underlying data.
Because scores are calculated by a back-end process, it can be
difficult to tell
why a given record has a given score.
And finally, the scale of the collection means that even large
projects don't tend to move the absolute numbers a lot.
And so this is an example of what I mean by that last bullet
point. So these are the CEDARS scores for the Department of Mineral
Sciences over the past six years, from
2020 to 2025. And so we don't do a ton of
digitization, so we wouldn't necessarily expect huge swings.
But we do some work with enhancement especially, and
despite touching thousands of records and making pretty significant changes,
it just doesn't really show up all that well on the scale of the full collection.
So now I'm going to talk a little bit about MIDS and whether MIDS can help
alleviate some of these issues.
We've already talked some more to some in a previous talk about
MIDS. But these are the information elements
that MIDS uses to
assign scores like CEDARS. This is done via a
presence-absence check, so there's no real data quality check on these.
The
MIDS working group has defined scoring for
these three different disciplines, so including biology,
paleobiology, and geology.
And again, there's a lot of overlap between these,
but there are some things that are more important in some disciplines than others.
So for example, information about the collector and the collection date is
considered more important in biology, whereas geology needs
those stratigraphic context fields to give you information
about where in the geologic record a sample is from.
I'm going to talk a little bit comparing these two systems.
To do that, I've lined them up as
I show here. So where a CEDARS score of three
aligns with a MIDS score of one.
The semantics here aren't perfectly aligned.
The Smithsonian system is based on this idea of a standard
record that you can be better than or a little bit worse than, whereas
MIDS is more about building out a record.
But this is reasonably close
for what I'm intending to talk about.
So first, I want to talk a little bit about how departments mapped
their individual data.
So this is a heat map.
On the y-axis, we have MIDS information elements that also
appear in the Smithsonian's scoring system for natural
history. On the x-axis is the CEDARS
level for those scores.
Brighter values mean that more departments have assigned a given
information element to a given score.
So in this case, in the leftmost column, you can see that the Name column is
bright yellow. That means that there's good agreement among departments
that that's a core piece of metadata that's absolutely required for a
standard record.
By contrast, most departments classified media as an
enhancement,
something you can use to create an above standard record, which is a little bit
different from the MIDS approach, where it's considered to
be a more fundamental part of the digitization process.
There's also some elements that appear in some department
scores that do not appear in MIDS, and those are primarily
internal data elements like storage location or
accession number.
When we compare the two scoring systems, we see some
significant differences between them.
So this is a plot of departmental CEDARS
scores and MIDS scores, and so it's the same underlying data
with the scores aligned as I discussed previously.
The black dots are the CEDARS scores, the white dots
are the MIDS scores.
And so what we can see on this plot is that there's a lot of variability
in these CEDARS scores because of how these rule sets have been defined,
whereas the MIDS scores cluster a lot more tightly around
three.
And so MIDS, because it's a consistent definition,
indicates that really,
this variability we're seeing in CEDARS doesn't really have a lot to do with the
underlying data.
By contrast, the MIDS scores are pretty tightly clustered
right around three
for CEDARS or one for MIDS, which means they might not be super
sensitive except to pretty big changes in the data
completeness. And that's largely to do with a big jump between
MIDS one and MIDS two scores in terms of the expected data.
Finally, I'm going to use the last couple minutes to talk about using metrics in
large collections.
I think there's a lot of potential for using something like MIDS or even our CEDARS
scores for organizing work in the collections, for deciding what
data's worth capturing,
what data might not be being exported when we submit data to GBIF or other
systems,
what records we need to improve.
And I think the way to approach this is less through the raw scores and more
through
some of the
element breakouts.
So this is a tool called MIDS Calculator.
This is available at the link below that's on the slide, and this
allows you to break out the specific elements that
are present in your records.
And so I've done that here for mineral sciences and paleobiology.
And so what I would say is that mineral sciences has
excellent completeness up through
MIDS one, but then drops off pretty significantly, particularly for stratigraphic
context, which is only present in a very small fraction of our records.
Whereas paleo has some issues with some of the core data.
For example, name and object type are
absent pretty frequently. License is a mapping issue.
Don't worry about that one.
But there is much better
coverage at higher levels for these geologic elements that are also part of the
standard.
I'm going to show two more plots. They're going to be heat maps like this one.
So this is a plot using the same color scheme as the
previous heat map. We have, in this case, the MIDS
information elements are on the X-axis, and the decade
at which the specimen was added to the collection is on the Y-axis,
and this is for the mineral sciences.
This is primarily to show that the metadata
is consistent in terms of when
material is added to the collection, so it's not like as we see more recent
acquisitions with much better metadata.
And also to show that the lack of stratigraphic context is
pretty much an intrinsic feature of the data that we're getting.
We just are typically getting between 5% and
20%, which
is actually significantly higher than the average.
So it's just very low, and it indicates that if we're going to use this for a
digitization project, we are at least internally going to need to settle
on some sort of system to either signify null
values that have been checked but no data is present or to just mark
records with an expected level of completeness.
And I know that this is stuff that the MIDS group has talked about,
but
in practical terms it's going to be very important for us.
And finally, I wanted to highlight some work that paleobiology
has done recently. I mentioned earlier that
the CEDARS statistics are tracked via what's called a primary
collection. So Paleo has recently revamped their collections
to focus more on manageable units of work that
needs to be done.
And so this is a sample of them. There are many more collections than this.
But some of the things that you can see on this diagram that might be helpful for
scoping work is one, for example, the name data,
where roughly 20% of Paleo's records are lacking a taxonomic
name. We can see that this is distributed largely in specific
collections,
which might be a good target
to work on. We can see that object type is pretty consistently absent,
and that's likely to be a mapping issue that can be addressed with some of the work
that Holly is doing and presented on earlier and will be presenting
on later in the conference on Thursday.
But also that there is significant variability
in many of these elements.
But I think this information level, element level view could be
useful for finding collections where we can
improve the quality of the records more easily and for targeting our work
in that way.
And that is all I have, so if you have any questions, I'm happy to take them.
And thank you for listening.
Is that it? Are you done? I have a couple.
I have a little housekeeping I want to
just- Go for it. Thank you ... if I can find it, because I need
to find it. I just wanted to- Oh ... A, thank everyone for- I got you ...
coming along and just give you an overview of the actual
collections descriptions interest group,
because it is in need of some people to check out that slide right
there.
That slide. All right.
Yeah. So just so that you know, for those of you who are either new to TADWIG or
have often been confused by this, TADWIG has
three ways that you can interact with
the standards work that it does. The interest group is
for anyone. If you have ideas, you have thoughts, there's something about
a particular topic, and there's an interest group, you can just
throw a question up there. What happens after that
is if that question and that topic turns into a piece of work that
needs to be done or that the community wants to be done, what happens is a task
group gets spun up to do a particular thing.
So for example, MIDS folks, they're a task group.
They are
getting the
MIDS standard to ratification. Once a standard
is ratified, it then becomes a maintenance group.
So if you're thinking about Darwin Core, it's been around for a long time.
It's been ratified. Every now and again, it has a task group that spins up,
that does a thing
Once that's done, the task group finishes, and then they move back
into maintenance group mode. So if you're interested in any of these levels, in any
of the groups, please get in touch with folks.
You don't have to do anything in here.
You just have to have good ideas and talk about things at this point.
Here, you're vested and you want to see something happen.
Down there, you want to see something evolve.
So I just wanted to put that up there as a
heads up.
All of the groups will take you. We'd love to hear what you have to say.
It's really interesting. The more voices in any of these groups, the better.
So
that's where I want to leave it. Ben?
Good.
I think we're good. So thank you for being here, and good luck
with the rest of HadWig.
And we're done. We made it through the day. We survived.
We did it.